<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VVhether it be a mortall sinne to transgresse ciuil lawes which be the commaundementes of ciuill magistrates. The iudgement of Philip Melancton in his epitome of morall philosophie. The resolution of D. Hen. Bullinger, and D. Rod. Gualter, of D. Martin Bucer, and D. Peter Martyr, concernyng thapparrel of ministers, and other indifferent thinges.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10391.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854774</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20218</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20218)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 975:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>VVhether it be a mortall sinne to transgresse ciuil lawes which be the commaundementes of ciuill magistrates. The iudgement of Philip Melancton in his epitome of morall philosophie. The resolution of D. Hen. Bullinger, and D. Rod. Gualter, of D. Martin Bucer, and D. Peter Martyr, concernyng thapparrel of ministers, and other indifferent thinges.</title>
                  <author>Melanchthon, Philipp, 1497-1560. aut</author>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575. aut</author>
                  <author>Gwalther, Rudolf, 1519-1586. aut</author>
                  <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551. aut</author>
                  <author>Parker, Matthew, 1504-1575. Briefe examination for the tyme, of a certaine declaration. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>101, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Powles Churchyarde by Richard Iugge printer to the Queenes Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1570?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>"Collates A-F G⁴, of which B7-C7 is reprinted in 4058 and anr. trans. is printed in 4062; D1-G4 is reprinted from 10387."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 22572.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 22572 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20218:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20218:1"/>
            <p>VVhether it be mortall ſinne to tranſgreſſe ciuil lawes, which be the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of ciuill Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The iudgement of Philip Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton in his Epitome of morall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reſolution of .D. Hen. Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and D. Rod. Gualter, of .D. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Bucer, and .D. Peter Martyr, <hi>concernyng thapparrel of Miniſters, and other indifferent thinges.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20218:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20218:2"/>
            <head>Whether it be mortall ſinne to tranſgreſſe Ciuil lawes, whiche be the commaundementes of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Magiſtrates?</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Orall vertue requireth not onlye to reſtraigne outwardly the handes, and to rule externall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but alſo it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the minde a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and an intent of counſayle: It alſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a mynde inured to holde in all braydes, &amp; to vſe a certayne moderation to deliberate. Theſe two thynges are truely required to vertues, and youth muſt be trayned vp, to vnderſtande the force and nature of eyther of them. Deliberation or aduiſement, muſt ſeke out and vnderſtande the cauſes and reaſons of al actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which (as it were with a bridle) drawe backe the furious mind into the right way, and ſhewe what is to be done.</p>
            <p>But morall is called that facilitie of the mynde, or equabilitie, moderation, and ſtay, wherwith it can reſtraigne it ſelf, vntyl that it be well aduiſed of the matter, to do that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20218:3"/> whiche is moſt ryght, with a certayne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>Seyng then it is nedeful to vnderſtand the cauſes of honeſt actions, it is not inough to knowe the lawes, but it is moſt neceſſarie to the perfourmance of morall vertue, to know what the aucthoritie of the lawes be, howe farre it is nedefull to obey them. The minde beyng with this doctrine eſtabliſhed, ſhall both thinke more honorablye of the lawes, &amp; alſo vnderſtande howe farre foorth it muſte obey. This iudgement of the aucthoritie of lawes parteyneth to morall vertue.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt I aunſwere, that to breake ciui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> lawes, or the preceptes of ciuill Magiſtrates is mortall ſinne, though there be no matter of offence:<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> for Paul ſayth playnely, that we muſt needes obey, not for feare of vengeance onlye, but alſo becauſe of conſcience, that is, that we not only feare ciuill puniſhment, but alſo know that our conſcience is made gilty, yf we do not obey. Nowe it is the part of a good mynd to conſyder, how great this band of obedience and common quietnes is, which God alſo requireth, that we obey lawes and Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>And yf we obey not, he ſayth that he wyll reuenge it. And God truely puniſheth both
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20218:3"/> in this lyfe, &amp; alſo after this life,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> as the fourth precept ſpeaketh of puniſhments in this lyfe. If thou wilt liue long vpon earth. &amp;c. for that precept geueth charge of obedience, that we obey not only our parentes, but alſo all them to whom our parentes do geue their auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, to wit, the magiſtrates. And therefore many other ſentences in the ſcripture,<note place="margin">Prou. 24.</note> ſpeake of the puniſhmentes that ſhalbe ſuffered in this lyfe. Feare God and the kyng, and haue no felowſhip with the ſeditious, for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhal come ſodenly. And Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> He whiche taketh the ſworde in hande, ſhall periſhe with the ſworde: for to take a ſworde in hande, ſignifieth to take vp the ſworde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the lawes and the Magiſtrates, that is, to be ſeditious, and to diſobey the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Magiſtrates. And the examples ſet out in the ſcriptures, do not only ſhewe this, but alſo the hiſtories of all ages, that murderers, theefes, periured perſons, vniuſt iudges, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious and tyrauntes, are for the moſt part puniſhed by God in this lyfe. This I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this ende, that we may knowe, howe that God requireth this diſcipline, to kepe men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>awe with feare of puniſhment.</p>
            <p>This feare encreaſeth reuerence toward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he lawes, and cauſeth ſome moralitie in our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20218:4"/> myndes, when as it brydleth as it were our luſtes, and inureth them to obedience. And there is no doubt, but that many gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous chaunces are puniſhments of this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous libertie, whiche many take vppon them, and wil not be ruled by the aucthoritie of the ſuperiours. For the law of God erreth not, which ſaith, Honor thy father &amp; mother, if thou wilt liue lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth. Beſides that, there is more reuerence in our mindes, when as we beleue, that the breache of the lawes is puniſhed with eternall tormentes after this lyfe, except we do repent. This ſentence tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the precepts of magiſtrates muſt wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be vnderſtand, namely of thoſe preceptes, which byd vs not to do agaynſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of God. We muſt alſo conſyder, whether it be wantonnes in them which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey, or whether ſome cauſes happen, which haue ſome excuſe. The differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon vſeth, lyketh me, who diſcerneth lawes, ſaying, That ſome are made for neceſſitie ſuch as ſerue for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon quietnes, as of theft, murder, mariages, diuiding of inheritaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, tributes, warfare, iudgements, and ſuch like. Some are not made ſo much for neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as for comlyneſſe, as it is prouided, that a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marry not, before ſhe haue left mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for her former huſband.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20218:4"/>
            <p>This difference liketh me, not only becauſe reaſon breadeth ſundry bondes, but rather, becauſe the mynde of the magiſtrate is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, which in the former matters ſimply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth obedience: in other lighter matters it doth not ſo exacte it. The mynde of the lawemaker muſt be conſydered, howe farre he wyll binde, &amp; yet in theſe lyghter thinges there may be no wantonneſſe &amp; contempt of aucthoritie, for it is an euyll example. But it is profitable as well for diſcipline, as the quietneſſe of the common wealth, ſo to accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome our myndes, that euen in trifles they may regard the aucthoritie of the lawes. And this we muſt knowe, that we lyue not to our ſelues, but to the common wealth. We muſt therfore take heede, that our examples be no publike hurt. The ſame doth Plato moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely wryte in his fift booke of lawes, that he is the beſt and moſt worthy citizen, which accounteth not triumphes or any victories to be the chiefeſt renowme in the citie, but to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell others in diligent obeying of the lawes.</p>
            <p>But here the queſtion is aſked, whether the like iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be of Eccleſiaſtical ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which by the aucthoritie of man are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned. I anſwer, that herein this rule muſt be obſerued, that in caſe of offence it is ſinne
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20218:5"/> to breake them, but no offence beyng geuen, they may be broken without mortall ſynne. For it is nedefull to kepe this doctrine, that ſuch ceremonies are thynges indifferent, &amp; not neceſſary for righteouſnes before god, as it is indifferent to weare a gowne or a cloke &amp;c. This rule of Paul is profitable both to common peace and the quietneſſe of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, for it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerueth publike rites, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to beware of offences, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon tumultes, and publike diſturbing of orders. Agayne it deliuereth the conſcience from many ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious opinions, and horrible crueltie: for yf good myndes do thinke that the obſeruyng of ſuch orders is neceſſarie (no cauſe of offence beyng) it wylbe a harde bondage.</p>
            <p>In ſo great a number of rytes, howe ofte ſhal our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences fal? ſometime in faſtings, in rehearſyng of prayers, in kepyng of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, or ſuche like: many thinges happen to them, eſpecially which haue buſineſſe, why they can not alwayes obſerue theſe orders. Therefore this rule contayneth a profitable moderation, whiche forbiddeth publique of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, preſerueth cuſtomes profitable for quietnes, and priuatly deliuereth the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences from daunger.</p>
            <p>When the cauſes of theſe lawes and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20218:5"/> are vnderſtande, good natures wyll the more embrace the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then is it fit that theſe thinges be knowen, namely that theſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are appoynted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church for good and publique orders ſake, &amp; that the Church wyll not priuatly entangle any mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. And moſt morall it is to loue common quietneſſe and order, good men therfore wyl greatly embrace theſe ordinances, ſeyng that to quietneſſe and order they are auayleable, &amp; in that they are deliuered from ſuperſtitious opinions, and knowe that without daunger theſe ceremonies may be left, no offence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng geuen.</p>
            <p>But here it is aſked, whether Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ordinaunces, and the ciuill lawes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates do diuerſly bynd. I aunſwere. The bonde is vnlyke: and although reaſons may be aſked, yet the playneſt way is to iudge theſe thinges by the euident &amp; cleare teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſcripture. Firſt therefore I wyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe them, then wil I adde the reaſons and interpretation, leſt any abſurditie may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by our opinion.</p>
            <p>Touching obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce due to the ciuil lawes, Paul ſayth, we muſt obey,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> not only for feare of vengeaunce, but alſo for conſcience ſake. This commaundement byndeth vs euen
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20218:6"/> without matter of offence: for we muſt obey the aucthoritie of God, though no offence be geuen.<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. Galat. 5.</note> But touchyng Eccleſiaſticall ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Paul ſayth, Let no man condemne you for meate or drinke, or a peece of an holy day. And againe, Stand faſt in the libertie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt hath made vs free, and wrap not your ſelues agayne in the yoke of bondage. And Chriſt ſayth,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note> That whiche entreth into the mouth, defileth not the man, &amp; the apoſtle excuſeth them, whiche breake traditions.</p>
            <p>Becauſe it is nedefull that this doctrine be in the Church, that thoſe traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s touching meate and ſuch lyke are no worſhypping or ryghteouſnes,<note place="margin">Not of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie in them ſelfe: But for neceſſitie of obedience.</note> but thinges indifferent: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the goſpel teacheth, that our conſciences may not be burdened with the opinion of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. Notwithſtandyng, becauſe this lyfe can not lacke ordinaunces &amp; ceremonies, this moderation is needefull, to haue them ſo obſerued, leſt the doctrine of true worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng and of the benefit of Chriſte ſhoulde be darkened. Agayne, leſt our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences ſhould be burdened with infinite vexations, which might cauſe ſhipwracke of fayth? Therefore the Goſpell wyll haue vs vnderſtande that theſe rytes may be left out, without matter of offence be geuen, but for good order, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20218:6"/> for auoydyng of offences, they ought to be kept. This libertie beyng lymited by the aucthoritie of the Goſpell, can not be taken away by mans aucthoritie.</p>
            <p>I haue ſhewed by the teſtimonies of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the bynding is vnlike. This is the playneſt aunſwere vnto this queſtion, but we wyll ſhewe the reaſon.</p>
            <p>The firſte is taken of the efficient cauſes, or the ryght of power, and this Gerſon folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth. The Ciuill magiſtrate by Gods auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, hath ryght to make honeſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable lawes, in thoſe matters whiche par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne to the defence of this corporall life and ciuil ſocietie, as of iudgements, the penalties of offences, contractes, ſucceſſions, and ſuche lyke, as Salomon ſayth,<note place="margin">Pro. 8.</note> By me kinges do raigne, and appoynt iuſt thinges.</p>
            <p>But Eccleſiaſtical power is limited, ſo as it hath a commaundement what it ought to teache, and that it inuent no newe worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng, neyther burthen the conſciences with traditions of ceremonies. For Peter ſayth, Why tempt you God, laying on a yoake. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> And Paul, Why make you decrees?<note place="margin">Colo. 2.</note> touche not, handle not. &amp;c. Seing then that the right of eyther power is vnlyke, the lawes alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly do bynde.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20218:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Second reaſon, of the final cauſes of lawes. Ciuil lawes, are the bands of common ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, therefore in breakyng them, charitie is alwayes hurt, for becauſe euery one ought to vſe his obedience, as a ſeale, to the defence of common quietnes, alſo the common tributes and al his trauayle muſt thereto be applyed: when this thei do not, thei deceaue the reſt, &amp; enioy other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s offices, imploying nothing of their owne vnto it, euen as he whiche to a common banket geueth not his money, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guileth the geſtes.</p>
            <p>The example alſo in breaking it doth hurt, and troubleth common quietneſſe: therefore in ciuill lawes, reſpect of charitie and offence is alwayes of force.<note place="margin">Ciuill lawes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall may ſometimes be broken.</note> But moſt part of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are priuate, &amp; domeſticall obſeruations, the breach wherof hurteth not others. Then ſeyng in them is no hazarde of charitie, nor offences chaunce, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aucthoritie of theſe lawes is vnlyke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or of theſe alſo we haue ſpoken, that then they are neceſſary, neither can they be broken without ſinne, when as the breach breadeth offences, that is, hurteth others mens fayth and maners, or raſhly troubleth the quietneſſe of others. And although it be profitable to conſider theſe reaſons &amp; cauſes, and to vnderſtande the degrees of lawes: yet
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20218:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> is it more ſure playnelye to geue iudgement out of theſe ſentences of ſcripture before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the reaſons haue many doubtes, &amp; do not ſufficiently ſtabliſhe the conſcience. And wyſe men may ſeeke and inuent many darke matters on both ſydes, if that we ſhall iudge only vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſons, &amp; not out of the ſcriptures. But here young men are to be warned, that although it be needefull to knowe, that theſe indifferent thynges are no worſhippyng of God: yet they muſt learne, that the caſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is large, and with diligent care they muſt beware of it: for in the breache of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions two thynges are hazarded, diſcipline, and tranquilitie, or the agreement of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. It is fit for vs to vnderſtande cheefly the greatneſſe and force of eyther of theſe, beyng occupied in the ſtudies of lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng and vertues.</p>
            <p>Firſte for diſcipline ſake, there neede cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ordinances: for vnſkilful perſons, muſt be accuſtomed to ceremonies and rites, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dayes, to certayne readinges, to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uate and publique exerciſes, &amp; for that cauſe Paul calleth the lawe a ſchoolemaiſter: for theſe ceremonies are certayne inſtitution<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for young yeres.</p>
            <p>And although the Goſpell doth bryng a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20218:8"/> higher doctrine, yet it wyll not haue diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and inſtitution to be aboliſhed, but it commaundeth that men be reſtraygned, ruled, and taught with ſuche inſtructions. What profite this diſcipline hath, I haue ſhewed els where: for God is effectual in the whiche are tractable to be taught and reſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not his word. Wherfore the example hurteth in the breache of traditions, for the common people, which naturally hateth the bands of lawes, willingly foloweth theſe examples, and therof taketh contempt of the whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and of all the lawes. Theſe ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beyng aboliſhed, there can be no diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, neyther can youth and the vnlearned people be taught.</p>
            <p>Then of neceſſitie muſt folowe exceedyng barbarouſnes, and deſtruction, where youth &amp; the common people can not be inſtructed. Howe great a wickednes and murther is it, to geue ſuche examples, whereby this deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation may ariſe? And in the other part of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, how much euyll is it, that the quietnes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church &amp; common weale is troubled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>In this corporal lyfe we haue neede of ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies for order ſake, or for decency, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for man is moſt ſemely. For if this order b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſanull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, infinite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion doth folowe. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20218:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> where there is no aucthoritie of teachers, no certayne tymes to teache, no certayne tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, no certayne forme of doctrine: in ſuch confuſion, neyther can the Goſpell be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, neyther the Churche inſtructed.</p>
            <p>Finally, as order &amp; conſent of publike ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances doth ioyne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in felowſhip together: ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of order doth ſeparate me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s minds breadeth horrible tumultes, &amp; endles warre.</p>
            <p>Let vs then thinke, that in breache of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, the example commonly and eaſyly ſpreadeth abroade amongſt others. Let vs conſyder, what euil is in an example. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leſt we burthen our conſciences with daunger, leſt we hurt others, let vs obſerue with greater care the publique ordinaunces whatſoeuer. It is tyrannical to regarde more what delighteth our ſelues, then what may do good to others: for we are not borne vnto our ſelues: but our lyfe parteyneth vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, eſpecially vnto the Churche, that is, to the glorie of Chriſt, to the conſeruation of the miniſterie, and the retayning of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline for the people. Theſe two things whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are the greateſt, the Churche deſyreth cheefly to defende. Herein let vs ſhewe our obedience, our diligence and endeuour, for the common quietneſſe and health of vs all.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20218:9"/> Plato ſayth, we muſt loue our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then our mother, becauſe our countrey is a certayne heauenly thyng. But the Churche ought to be our true countrey, and this true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is heauenly: for it is the Temple of God, and the congregation of the members of Chriſte. Wherefore this we muſt loue, and wyllyngly obey it, and yeelde much vnto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> profit &amp; tranquilitie therof.<note place="margin">Galat. 4.</note> Paul calleth tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, beggerly elements: which although they be beggerlye, that is, ſmall thynges, tranſitorie, not eternal, they are no worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng, they are no ryghteouſnes, yet they are elementes, that is, ordinaunces, whiche this corporal lyfe can not wante, becauſe of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and good orders ſake. Wherfore thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ordinaunces are not to be diſanulled, but Paules counſaile muſt be conſydered, who although he cal them beggerly, yet he calleth them elementes, &amp; ſo taketh away the prayſe of ryghteouſneſſe, ſhewing ſtyl that there be ordinaunces, which haue their profite. Great is the for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of diſcipline, there is no ſweeter harmonye, then good order in a common wealth. Therfore theſe are called elementes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, ordinaunces, whiche preſerue tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> harmonie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20218:9"/>
            <head>Philip Melancton vppon the .xiii. Chapter of Paules Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET euerye ſoule be ſubiect vnto the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gher powers: for there is no power but of GOD. The powers that be, are ordained of God. VVhoſoeuer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God: &amp; thei that reſiſt, ſhall receaue to them ſelues damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For rulers are not fearefull to good workes, but to the euyl. VVylt thou not feare the power, do well, &amp; thou ſhalt haue prayſe of the ſame: for he is the miniſter of God for thy wealth. But if thou do euil, feare: for he beareth not the ſworde in vayne: for he is the miniſter of God, reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20218:10"/> of wrath on him that doth euyll. VVherefore ye muſt needes be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte, not onely for feare of puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but alſo becauſe of conſcience &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ende of this precept ſtandeth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion, &amp; the propoſition repeated againe. <hi>(That of neceſſitie we muſte obey)</hi> And that certaynely for conſcience ſake, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onely for the penaltie.</p>
            <p>This addition or exaggeration muſte b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diligently conſydered. He that is taken of a theefe, yf he can auoyde hym, eſcapeth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence. But contrary, yf any man could caſt from him ſuch charges as the magiſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commaundeth, yet he cannot reiect them without ſinne, without the magiſtrate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth thereto, for that we be neceſſarily<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bounde to the magiſtrates, and alſo for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>Some teachers haue holden in diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the preceptes of the magiſtrate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do not bynde to mortall ſinne, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mere man cannot inflicte a payne eternall But the errour of theſe men, is playnly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>futed by the teſtimonie of ſaint Paul, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20218:10"/> ſayth, <hi>VVe muſt be ſubiect, not onely for penaltie, but alſo for conſcience,</hi> that is, leſt our conſcience ſhoulde be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with mortall ſinne. <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is mortall ſinne, to breake the ſtatutes of the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, for that God hath made vs ſubiect to magiſtrates, and he layeth his puniſhment vpon ſuche as contemne the magiſtrate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe therein alſo the aucthoritie of God is contemned.</p>
            <p>And here may it appeare, that in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell the aucthoritie of the magiſtrate is more confirmed and defended, than in any other doctrine: for no other doctrine ſo earneſtly byndeth men to obedience. For the Goſpell doth commaunde obedience, not onely for corporall or temporall paynes, but alſo to eſcape the wrath of God, an eternall payne, and there is no bonde greater than this bonde of conſcience. Therefore <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror Iulian,</hi> and ſuche other, dyd great wrong to the Goſpell, when they wrote that the doctrine of the Goſpell diſſolueth pollicie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for this cauſe pay you tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, for thei are Gods miniſters, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for the ſame purpoſe. Gyue to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20218:11"/> euery man therefore his duetie, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, to whom tribute is due, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, to whom cuſtome, Feare, to whom feare, Honor, to whom honor belongeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before he ſpake generally of obedience, nowe he addeth the ſpeciall kyndes thereof, in commaundyng to yeelde three thinges, to wit, tribute, feare, and honor. Tribute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth all externall burdens whiche b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> due: as impoſitions, cuſtomes, diligence, marſhall exerciſe, &amp; ſuch lyke ſeruices eyther of body or of goodes. For why? the common wealth can not be defended, vnleſſe the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces receaue ayde of the laboure and charge of the ſubiectes. Therefore in this place Paul affirmeth tribute &amp; cuſtome to be due, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that therfore you do pay tribute, for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the miniſters of God (namely for their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, which is the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth) be occupied: but this preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſketh the helpe both of ſouldiers and other ſeruitours, not onely in warre, but alſo in peace. Although (conſidering indifferent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly) we finde that euery magiſtrate continual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly do warre, whyleſt he puniſheth runne gates, theeues and pickers. And for ſo muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20218:11"/> as ſuch people as theſe, can not be ſuppreſſed without the helpe of ſouldiers, and citizens: By duetie we are bound to the maintenance of ſuche aſſiſtaunce, to make contribution, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greatnes of the daunger doth ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, to miniſter our further helpe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in that behalfe. And as officers ſent to apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d runagates, are bound faithfully to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: ſo ſouldiers in time of warre, their cities being beſeeged, are bound faithfully to defend the holdes committed to their charge to the vttermoſt that they may. In this kind of duetie, deſerueth great commendations my countrie Bruta, ſituate aboue Spires, in the territorie of the prince Palatine. For it was defended by the citizens, with loyall ſayth &amp; great conſtancie, twiſe within theſe fewe yeres. Firſte, in the yere of our Lorde 1504. beyng violently aſſaulted more then a moneth together by a valiaunt armie of the Switzers. After that, of late in the yere of our Lorde. 1525. whan the vplandiſhe people had ſtirred vp an horrible commotion, and had moued ſedition generallye throughout all Germanie, at what tyme my countreyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned in their allegeances towardes their princes. And wheras the rebels had aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20218:12"/> out of the landes of Spira &amp; Whiten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berg, on both ſides of the towne, to ſpoile th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> marchaundize, whiche were then to be car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ried from Franckford into Sweuia (becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that theſe rebelles had made the paſſage daungerous) theſe marchaundizes were left with vs, and committed to the fidelitie &amp; v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liantnes of our countreyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In this daunge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the fayth &amp; courage of my countreymen dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt manifeſtly appeare: for both thoſe fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous rebelles were repelled by force of arme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the towne, &amp; thoſe goodes (committe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to their cuſtodie) were to their great com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendation defended agaynſt all violence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feare and Honor,</hi> parteyneth to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mynde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feare,</hi> ſignifieth obedience from the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honor,</hi> ſignifieth not onely extern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reuerence, but alſo a reuerence in the conſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence. And here is a difference betwixt Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian men, and wicked men. For wicked me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do onely feare the ciuill puniſhmentes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this feare is ſoone ſlypped out of euyll men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heartes: but Chriſtian men do truely fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the magiſtrate, becauſe they feare God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for that they knowe hym to reuenge all con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20218:12"/> agaynſt the magiſtrate. Wycked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en ſhewe outwardlye the ſignes of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, but inwardlye they thynke very yll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the magiſtrates, as the Philoſophers do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtifye in their bookes, holdyng by diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, that the publique ſtate of gouernement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s but mere tyrannye. But the Chriſtian men do truely geue honor to the magiſtrate: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd herein ſtandeth honour, to attribute to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem power, liberalitie, wyſedome, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tice. And wheras Chriſtian men be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, that all power is ordeyned of God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat it is maintayned from God aboue, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cknowledge that power, and thinke that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey be bounde to geue place, and ſubmit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemſelues therunto. And they alſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edge that bounteouſneſſe, becauſe they ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat mankinde hath hygh corporal benefites <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the magiſtrate, that is to ſay, peace, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their owne life, of their wiues, of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hyldren, and quietneſſe to ſeeke for their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yng, to learne religion, and other good ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nces. Theſe be thoſe great benefites, ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o greater ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be expreſſed in worldly cauſes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or theſe, chriſtian men geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to god, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecauſe that he graunteth theſe thinges by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he magiſtrate. And agayne of their partie,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20218:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20218:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20218:14"/> they ſhewe thankfulneſſe towarde the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. And whereas they be perſwaded that this power is ruled from God aboue, &amp; that theſe benefites be geuen from thence, they pray to God for the magiſtrate, that he woulde vouchſafe to gouerne him, &amp; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the publique peace: for they know, that not onely wicked men, but alſo the deuyll himſelfe, lay in waight againſt princes, and that without ceaſing, they practiſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all mankinde. Therefore this is the chiefe honor, whiche the onely chriſtian man attributeth to the magiſtrate, that is to ſay, Thankes geuing to our God, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the magiſtrate. As <hi>Hieremie</hi> geueth ſpeciall precept in this cauſe, that the Iewes in their exile would pray for the kyng of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, &amp; all his whole kingdome. And Paul biddeth that we ſhoulde pray for the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> And verily there is no greater or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementer exerciſe of fayth amongſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny publique perils, than prayer for publique peace. And it is our part to vnderſtand thoſe peryls, and to iudge them to parteyne to our ſelfe. Furthermore, the chriſtians attribut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the magiſtrates, wyſedome, and iuſtice, that is, they do not preferre their priuate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20218:14"/> iudgementes, before the lawes and decrees of the magiſtrate: but obey them. Thei quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell not with them, they do not diſanull the lawes: and this honor is moſt neceſſarie to the pulique peace, not to vſe cauillation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the lawes, nor enuiouſly to interpret the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Moreouer, hereto it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to couer, to excuſe, and to mitigate, the ouerſightes of the lawes &amp; of the magiſtrates. This courteous interpretation, as it is neceſſarie in our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation, ſo much more is it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in publike ſocietie towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate, as it is written, <hi>Loue beareth al things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and loue is the bonde of perfection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.</note> 
               <hi>to preuent all diſſolutions of the common wealth.</hi> Agayne,<note place="margin">Iames, 5. 1. Pet. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Loue co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the multitude of ſinnes.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Obei your magiſtrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> 
               <hi>though they be rigorous.</hi> Rude and vnſkilfull men, are dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to be admoniſhed in this, that they quarrel not, nor chaunge the lawes and publique inſtitutions. Father Noe dyd curſe his ſonne Cham, for that he vncouered hym and ſcorned hym: and euen ſo let them be aſſured whiche depraue the lawes, they which malitiouſly make the worſt of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20218:15"/> ouerſightes, that they be curſed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, and ſhalbe puniſhed for this offence, for that they geue not due honor to the lawes and magiſtrates, and this ſlaunderous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of lawes, ought the rather to be eſchewed, becauſe it bringeth foorth horribl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commotions in the common wealth. As <hi>Xenophon</hi> prudently ſayth, <hi>Al innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, to be very daungerous.</hi> And <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, <hi>As a man ought not to vſe any violence to his father, beyng in dotage, ſo lykewyſe ſhould there no extremitie be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey in their weakenes. For it is impoſſible, that great altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in common wealthes, ſhoulde be ended without manſlaughter.</hi> Howbeit, when the magiſtrate doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, that we ſhoulde our ſelues do any thyng agaynſt the precept of God, obedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not to be geuen, but in this caſe, the rule is to be folowed.<note place="margin">Actes. 5.</note> 
               <hi>VVe ought to obey god, more than men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:20218:15"/>
            <head>To the reuerende fathers in Chriſte D. Rob. Horne Biſhop of VVincheſter. D. Ed. Grindal Biſhop of London. D. Ioh. Parcuſte B. of Norwiche, his honorable Lordes, and moſt deare brethren in Englande.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Yght reuerende honorable Lordes and dearely beloued brethren, the Lorde Ieſus bleſſe you, and preſerue you from all euyll. We ſend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you here our opinion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters of apparrell, written to our worſhipfull frende maiſter. N. and maiſter. M. thoſe godly and learned men. And for that cauſe we ſende it vnto you, that you might vnderſtande, we deale not with our brethren priuily, without your knowledge, who are the principall and cheefe miniſters, and that ſo muche as in vs lyeth, we ſeeke the vnitie and concorde of your congregations, in all reſpectes. And we heartely beſeeche almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, to haue a ſpeciall regarde of your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20218:16"/> eſtate, and to continue you in one conſent an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnitie. We earneſtly exhort you, ryght ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norable and deare brethren, to be carefull fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe faythfull miniſters and learned men for they haue commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly their affections. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which cauſe the apoſtle warneth vs, that on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> helpe to beare anothers burthen. You ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by your aucthoritie do very muche with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt noble Lady your Queene: bryng it the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to paſſe with her Maieſtie, that our goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brethren may be reconciled &amp; reſtored again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And we alſo beſeeche that you. D. Horne, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good lorde, and deare brother, that as ſoon as theſe my letters may be deliuered, ye cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them to be ſent to the Biſhop of Norwiche, to communicate them to. D. Iuel, to. D. San<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, &amp; to. D. Pilkinton, to whom alſo I pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe to write at the next mart at Franckfort by gods grace. Theſe I haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in haſte aſwel in maiſter Gualters name, as in myn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne, ſendyng them to Baſile, from thenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be conueyed to Antwarpe. And we hartily deſire you to ſende vs word, whether ye hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receaued them or no. Fare ye well ryght re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerende fathers. The Lorde bleſſe you, and your labours.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Tigurine <date>this third of Maye. M.D.Lxvi.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>H. Bullinger your very frende.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20218:16"/>
            <head>To maiſter. N. and M.</head>
            <p>THE Lorde Ieſu bleſſe you right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful and welbeloued brethren, and preſerue you from all euyll. I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued your letters, in the whiche you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. ſeeme to complayne, that my aunſwere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto your queſtion was ouer ſhort and brief. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erily my brother, I ſaw no cauſe then, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her do I ſee any yet, why I ſhoulde haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritten thoſe letters any larger. For you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y required to knowe my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, touching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he matter of apparrel, for the which ye now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontende in England. Vnto which queſtion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thought I ſhould anſwere in few wordes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or ſo muche as in fewe wordes I coulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lare my iudgement. And then alſo I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>toode, that. D. Peter Martyr, of moſt happie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emembraunce, handled the ſame queſtion at Oxforde, and heare to many tymes at large, whereto I could ſay no more. And I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo, that in my letters vnto you, brother M. I made mention of my opinion herein. And that I may nowe ſpeake a worde or twaine what I thinke hereof: Surely, I like not in any wyſe, that (yf ye were commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) ye ſhoulde ſay ſeruice at an aulter, rather burthened, then beautified with the image of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20218:17"/> a crucifixe in maſſing apparrell, that is, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>albe,<note place="margin">Caſula.</note> &amp; in a veſtment, which hath the pict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt crucified ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyng on the backe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o farre as I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perceaue by my letters rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued out of Englande, there is no content<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now of any ſuch garment. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> queſtion</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether it be lawfull for Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel to weare a rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cap or a ſquare, or to put on a wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> robe called a ſurpleſſe, whereby t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſter may be decerned from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vulgare ſort? And whether a Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter ought rather to leaue his hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> callyng, then to weare ſuch apparre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touchyng whiche queſtion, I wrote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mynde the laſt mart, vnto the reuerende f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther my lorde. R. Horne B. of Wincheſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> briefly repeating. D. Martyrs wordes. M felowe miniſter and welbeloued Kynſma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> D. Rodolphe Gualter, wrote vnto hym al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not long before, a coppie wherof I ſende he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> incloſed vnto you, and to the reſt of our br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren. Wherfore, yf ye wyll heare vs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſirous to know our iudgement concernin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this matter of apparrell, as you ſignified v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me the laſt mart you were: loe you hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our iudgement in that Epiſtle, whervnto
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20218:17"/> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wyll not agree, we are heartily ſorie: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng we haue none other counſell, we moſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>artily and inceſſantly pray to god, who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all thynges, and at all tymes to be called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that he vouchſafe by his holy grace and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wer, to comfort and helpe our miſerable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate.</p>
            <p>You brother. N. propoſed a fewe ſuch que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons: but our brother. M. heaped together a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat many more of the ſame argument. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t I, according to my ſimple ſkil, did neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owe to haue matters diſtracted into ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ny queſtions, and to be entangled with ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any doubtes, which otherwyſe being more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gle by them ſelues, myght be more eaſyly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſolued: yet notwithſtanding, I wyl write <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wne a lytle to euerye one of them, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rein alſo I may ſatiſfie you my worſhipful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d deare brethren, as muche as lyeth in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder vtteraunce, &amp; rather dull, then quicke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſharpened wit. And I beſeeche you, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u woulde accept in good part this my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g, as of your brother, &amp; one that vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loueth you, &amp; to iudge therof with a quiet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynde, voyde of all affections. For my part vtterly abhorre all contentions, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re nothyng more humblye of almyghtie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, then that it might pleaſe him to remoue
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20218:18"/> all diſſention &amp; ſtrife farre from his Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whiche from the firſt beginning hath ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueylouſly hurt true godlynes, and as it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> torne and rent the Churche in peeces, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it neuer ſo quiet and floriſhing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhereas it is demaunded, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther lawes ought to be enioyned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſiaſticall perſons for weary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> apparrell, that thereby they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> knowen from the lay people.</hi> I au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere, that there is ambiguitie and doubt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the worde, <hi>ought:</hi> for in caſe it be vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtoode for that whiche is neceſſarie, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parteynyng to euerlaſtyng lyfe, I ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the lawmakers them ſelues do not ſo vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande or meane it. But yf it be ſayde that may be done for comlynes and decencie, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for dignitie and orders ſake, that it ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but a ciuill obſeruation, or ſome ſuche ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thyng, as is that wherein the apoſtle wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> haue the miniſter or Biſhop κόσμιον, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> modeſt, or comlye, I do not ſee howe he o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fendeth, which weareth ſuche a garment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is commaunded to weare it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether the ceremoniall attyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or worſhippyng of the Leuitica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20218:18"/> prieſthood, be to be brought agayne into the Church?</hi> I aunſwere, That yf a cap or a ſeemely garment, without ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be commaunded to be worne by a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, no wyſe man wyll ſaye, that right Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme is brought in agayne. Moreouer here I repeate the ſame, that I ſee Peter Martyr hath aunſwered, who when he had ſhewed how the ſacramentes of the olde lawe were quite aboliſhed, which we ought not to bring agayne into the Churche of Chriſte, hauing nowe Baptiſme and the Lordes Supper, in ſteede of them, thus he ſayth. There were notwithſtandyng in the Leuiticall lawe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne actions of that nature, whiche coulde not properly be called ſacramentes, for they ſerued to decencie, order, and ſome commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which as agreeable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght of nature, and alſo profitable for our commoditie, I ſuppoſe may both be brought in, and alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined. Who ſeeth not, that for mainteining peace, and for that the faythfull myght the better lyue together, the Apoſtles commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Gentiles to abſteyne from that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rangled, and from blood. No doubt theſe were thinges belongyng to the Leuiticall lawe. Furthermore, no man is ignoraunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at tithes are appoynted at this day to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyne
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20218:19"/> miniſters. It is euident that Pſalmes &amp; Hymnes are now ſonge in holy congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and meetinges, whiche notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng the Leuites alſo vſed. And that I le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not this paſſe neither, we haue holy dayes in remembraunce of Chriſtes reſurrection, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuche lyke. Shall all thoſe be aboliſhed, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe thei are tokens and reliques of the old<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lawe? You ſee therfore, al thinges of the Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitical lawe are not ſo abrogated, that non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them may be vſed. Thus farre. P. Martyr</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether we maye weare ſuche apparrell, as the papiſtes do?</hi> I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. We may, ſo long as it is not proued that the Pope brought in the differences o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> garments. Nay it is manifeſt, the differenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of apparrel is more ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then the Pope is Neyther do I ſee any cauſe, why we may no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> go as the papiſtes do in apparrell, whiche is not ſuperſtitious, but of pollicie, and for com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyneſſe ſake. If we ſhoulde haue nothyng common with them, then muſt we forſake a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Churches, refuſe all lyuinges, not mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter baptiſme, not ſay the Apoſtles or Nicen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> creede, yea and quite caſte away the Lorde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prayer. Neyther do you borowe any ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies of them. The matter of apparrell wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neuer taken away at the beginning of refo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20218:19"/> &amp; is yet reteyned, not by the Popes lawe, but by the kynges commaundement, as an indifferent thing of meere pollicie. Yea truely, if you weare a cap or a peculiar kynde of apparrell, as a ciuill and politike thing, it ſmelleth neyther of Iudaiſme, nor Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme: For theſe wil ſeeme to ſeparate them ſelues from the ciuill and common lyfe, and account a meritorious deede in the wearyng of a peculiar garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. So Euſtachius Biſhop of Sebaſtia, was not ſimply condemned for wearyng a peculiar kynde of garment: but for that he put religion in his garment. The cannons of the counſell of Gangren, Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen, and of the .vj. councell, are well knowen. If in caſe any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people be perſwaded that theſe thynges ſauour of Papiſme, Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, or Iudaiſme, let them be tolde the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, and perfectly inſtructed therein. And if ſo be, through the importunate crying out hereon before the people by ſome men, many be diſquieted in their conſcience, let them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware whiche ſo do, that they bring not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter yokes on their owne neckes, &amp; prouoke the Queenes Maieſtie, &amp; bryng many fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full miniſters in ſuche daunger, as they can not ryd them ſelues out of agayne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether theſe men, whiche hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20218:20"/> haue vſed their libertie, maye nowe with ſafe conſcience, bryng them ſelues and their Churche into bondage, through the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the prince?</hi> I aunſwere thus. I thinke thei ought to take heed, leſt by odious diſputing, exclaymyng, and ſtryuing for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell, and by this importunate dealyng, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion be offered to the princes Maieſtie, not to leaue the matter any le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in their choiſe, who haue hitherto vſed this libertie, &amp; that ſhe being incenſed with neceſſarie clamours, commaunde them eyther to weare that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrel, or to geue ouer their charges. Truely it ſeemeth very ſtraunge vnto me (be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, my worſhipful and deare brethren, with out your offence) that you ſo perſwade your ſelues, that you can by no meanes with a ſafe conſcience ſubmit your ſelues and your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations to the bondage of apparrell, and do not rather way with your ſelues, if ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to weare a thyng meere politike and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and odiouſly contende alwayes, vnto what maner of bondage you ſubmit your ſelues and your churches, who leauyng your charge, expoſe your Churches to Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, or at the leſt wiſe to vnfit teachers, who
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20218:20"/> are not ſo able to edifie the people, as ye your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elues are. Do you ſet your churches at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, when you miniſter occaſion to oppreſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem with more and with greater burthens? You knowe wel inough after what a great many ſeeke, how they are affected towardes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he preachyng of the Goſpell, and what they woulde proue, if they ſucceede you, and what we may hope for at their handes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether the apparrell of the Cleargie, be a thyng indifferent?</hi> Surely it ſeemeth to be an indifferent thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſo much as it is a mere ciuil thing, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for decency, ſeemelines, &amp; for order, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is put no religion. This muche I thought good to anſwer briefly vnto your queſtions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny learned and louing brother. N. Nowe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome to our brother. M. queſtions, in diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng whereof, perchaunce I wyll be more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riefe. <hi>VVhether a particuler kynde of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrel, differyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lay men, were euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppoynted for miniſters of the Churche? And whether in theſe dayes, it may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted in reformed Churches?</hi> I anſwere. That in the auncient Churche, there was a particuler faſhion of apparrell for Prieſtes. It appeareth in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtorie of Theodoret. li. 2. ca. 2. 7. &amp; of Socrat. li. 6. ca. 22.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20218:21"/> No man is ignorant, which hath but lightl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> read ouer the monumentes of the auncien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fathers,<note place="margin">Pallium</note> but that the miniſters vſed a cloke i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their ſeruice. And therfore I ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d before, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the diuerſitie of garmentes had not his or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginall of the Pope. Euſebius citeth out o the auncient writers, that S. Iohn the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ware on his head a leafe, or thinne plat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lyke vnto a Byſhoppes miter. And <hi>Pontiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diaconus</hi> witneſſeth of S. Cyprian the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr, that when he offered his necke to the ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner,<note place="margin">Birrum. Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica.</note> he firſt gaue hym his cap, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deacon his vpper garment, and ſo ſtoode ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parreled in white linnen. Moreouer, Chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoſtome maketh mention of whyte apparrel of miniſters. But it is certayne, that whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Chriſtians turned from their paganiſm to the Goſpell, in ſteade of gownes, they pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on clokes:<note place="margin">Pallium</note> for the which beyng afterwarde mocked of the infidels, Tertullian wrote very learned booke, <hi>De pallio.</hi> I could brin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more ſtuffe of this ſort, yf this ſuffiſed no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> In deede I had rather no apparrell wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> layde vpon the miniſters againſt their wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but that they vſed the cuſtome of the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles. But in ſo muche as the prince co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the cap, and the ſurpleſſe, wherein (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue often ſaide) ſhe putteth no religion, an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20218:21"/> ſithe the ſame thing hath ben vſed amongeſt the olde fathers without ſuperſtition, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whyle the Churche was as yet in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtate: I would not wiſhe good miniſters to account the forwardneſſe of religion to be cheefly in theſe thinges, but to yeelde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vnto the tyme, &amp; not to braule conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly in matters indifferent, but to iudge with modeſtie, that theſe things may be, and that we muſt go forewarde accordyng to the tyme: for they are nearer the Apoſtles ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, who know of no ſuch diſtinction, nor do vrge it, but yet in the meane whyle do not refuſe diſcipline in their apparrell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether the preſcribyng of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell, be agreeable with Chriſtian libertie?</hi> I anſwer. That indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t things may ſometymes be preſcribed, yea, and alſo conſtrayned to, as I may terme it, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the vſe, but not as of neceſſitie,<note place="margin">What is meant by neceſſitie.</note> that is, that any indifferent thyng of his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhoulde be forced to a mans conſcience, and thereby a kynde of religion charged to his conſcience. The times and places of holy aſſemblies, are rightly accounted to be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent: and yet if there be no order preſcribed therein, I pray you what confuſion and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order woulde ryſe hereby?</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20218:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether any new ceremonies may be increaſed, beſides the expreſſe worde of God?</hi> I aunſwere. That I like not with increaſing of new ceremonies, and yet I wyll not deny, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new may be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſo that there be no worſhippyng of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> placed in them, and that they be appoynted for order and diſcipline. Chriſte hym ſelfe ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated the feaſt or ceremonie of the dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Encoen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</note> &amp; yet we reade not, that the ſame feaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was commaunded by the lawe. To be ſhort, the greater part of thoſe propoſitions or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions touchyng matters of apparrell, do ſtande on this point. <hi>VVhether any lawe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought or may be made in the Churche, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching apparrel?</hi> And ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> queſtion is brought to this general propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, <hi>VVhat is lawful to be decreed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning ceremonies?</hi> Vnto theſe queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s I briefly anſwere. That I woulde haue no ceremonies brought into the Churche, but ſuch as are neceſſarie: yet in the meane ſeaſon I confeſſe, that the lawes touchyng theſe ceremonies, which perchance are not neceſſarie, &amp; ſometyme vnprofitable, may not by and by be condemned of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that factions and ſchiſmes be ſtirred vp in the Churche, for ſo muche as they are without ſuperſtition, and thinges of their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20218:22"/> owne nature meere indifferent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether it be lawfull to renue the cuſtomes of the Iewes, being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated, and to tranſlate the rytes proper to idolatrous religion from them, to be vſed in reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?</hi> Touching this queſtion, I anſwered before, when I ſpake of Leuiticall rites and ceremonies. But I wil not in any wyſe haue the ceremonies of Idolaters, not purged from their ſuperſtition &amp; errours, tranſlated into reformed Churches. And agayne on the other ſide, it may be aſked, whether the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued cuſtomes, after the ſuperſtition is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, may be for diſcipline and orders ſake, reteyned without ſinne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether conformitie or agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ceremonies, be to be required of neceſſitie?</hi> I anſwer. That the agreement of ceremonies in al Churches, peraduenture is not neceſſary. In the meane time, if a thing vnneceſſarie, whiche yet is not wycked, be commaunded, therefore we may not forſake the Church committed to our charge. There was not the like faſhion in ceremonies in all the auncient Churches: and yet thoſe which vſed conformable ceremonies, deſpiſed not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20218:23"/> thoſe whiche were without the ſame. I eaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beloue, that wyſe &amp; politike men do vrg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a conformitie in ceremonies, becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thinke this wyl mainteyne concorde, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe the Churche throughout all England is one; wherein if there be no wicked thyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mixt withall, I can not ſee howe you can e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiouſly obiect any thing agaynſt ſuche goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> orders.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether ceremonies ioyne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with open offence, maye be retay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned or no?</hi> I aunſwere. That all offence muſt be auoyded, but in the meane whyle, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt beware leſt we conceale, and cloke ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnder the colour of offence You knowe there is one kynde of offence g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, and an other kinde taken, and wylfull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> procured. Here I wyll not diſpute, whethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you without great offence geuen, can forſak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your Churches, for the whiche Chriſte dyed and that for a matter of indifferencie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether that any conſtitution of men, are to be tollerated in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Churche, which albeit they are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wicked of their owne nature, yet do helpe to edification neuer a whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> I anſwere. That yf the conſtitutions, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20218:23"/> the princes Maieſtie woulde enioyne you to, be without impietie, you muſt rather beare with them, then forſake your Churches. For if edifiyng the Churche, be cheefly to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered in this behalfe: ſurely then in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Churche, we ſhall more deſtroy it, then in wearing apparrell. And where there is no impietie, nor the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience is not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, there ought we not geue ouer our voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, although there be ſome kynde of ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude therby laied vpon vs. And in the meane tyme, it may be a queſtion, whether we may rightly comprehende the matter of apparrell vnder the name of bondage, in reſpect that it ſerueth for comlineſſe and order?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether the prince maye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe any thyng touchyng ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, without the wyll and free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Cleargie?</hi> I aunſwere. That if the prince ſhoulde alwayes tarrye for the conſent of the Cleargie: perchaunce thoſe moſt wyſe and godly kinges Ioſaphat, Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias, Aſa, and Ioſias, with other good prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhoulde neuer haue brought the Leuites, and Miniſters of the Churche, into good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Albeit I woulde not wiſhe in any wyſe, that Biſhops ſhoulde be excluded from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20218:24"/> concerning matters of the church Neyther woulde I agayne haue them cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge vnto them ſelues that power, which they vſurped agaynſt princes &amp; magiſtrate in the tyme of poperie. Lykewyſe I would not haue Biſhops kepe ſilence, and geue con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent to wicked ſtatutes of princes.</p>
            <p>The two latter queſtions touche the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter more narrowly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether it be more conuenien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſerue in the Church after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or rather therefore to be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of Eccleſiaſticall function?</hi> And agayne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether good paſtours may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iuſtlye put from the miniſterie, for ſuch kynde of ceremonies?</hi> I anſwere. That if there be no ſuperſtition in ſuche cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, nor any vngodlyneſſe, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng they are layed on good pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, which had rather thei were not ſo lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon them, I wyll graunt in deede, &amp; that franckly, that there is a burthen and a bon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dage layed on them, but yet I will not grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (for very good cauſes to) that therefore their charge and miniſterie is to be forſaken, and their place left vnto wolues, (as I ſayde be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20218:24"/> or to other vnmete miniſters: eſpecially, the the libertie of preachyng remayneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee, and that there be heede taken, leſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſeruitude be thruſt vpon them, with ſuche ther thinges of this nature.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I ſpoken thoſe thinges which I thought meete, concerning theſe propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed queſtions, knowyng right well that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her men accordyng to their learning, might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue diſcuſſed the matter muche better, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arre more eloquently. But becauſe it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our wylles I ſhoulde make aunſwere, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue done what I coulde, leauyng the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er free vnto other mens iudgement &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yng. That whiche remayneth, is, that I would not haue any mans conſcience vrged, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſnared: but I put foorth theſe thinges to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e examined, and I warne al men, that none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this controuerſie frame hym ſelfe a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, becauſe he wyl contende. And I alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you al in Chriſt Ieſu our Lorde, ſauiour of his Churche, our head &amp; kyng, that euery one of you deepely conſider with your ſelues, by which of theſe twayne he ſhall moſt edifie Chriſtes congregation: whether if for order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd comlyneſſe ſake, he vſe the apparrell as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing indifferent, which hytherto hath not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> litle ſet forewarde the vnitie and profite of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20218:25"/> the Church: or els whether for a matter of garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he leaue his Church to be poſſeſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if not of wolues, yet of verye vnmeete an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> naughtie miniſters. The Lorde Ieſu grau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you grace to ſee, vnderſtande, and folow th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whiche tendeth to the ſettyng foorth of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> glorie, and the Churches peace and tranqu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie. Fare ye well in the Lorde, with al oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> faythfull miniſters. We wyl pray diligent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vnto God, that ye may thinke and do the thinges whiche are wholeſome and holy. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Gualtherus commendeth him moſt hearti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vnto you, and wiſheth you all proſperitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do alſo the reſt of the miniſters.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gure <date>the Kalendes of May. The yere of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Lorde. M.D.Lxvj.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Henrie Bullinger, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſter of the Church at Tigure, in Maiſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gualtherus name an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his owne.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20218:25"/>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:20218:26"/>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:20218:26"/>
            <head>Doctiſſimo viro. D. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tino Bucero, Theologiae in Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia Cantabrigienſi profeſſori Regio, Thomas Cantua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienſis.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter my hartie ſalutations, ryght welbeloued Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Bucer, I haue read that booke which ye haue ſent to Doctour Peter Alexander, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie betwixt. M. Hoper and the Biſhop of London: in which booke, many thinges are learnedly declared, and largely diſputed. Wherfore now I pray you, that ye would ſend vnto me your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe queſtions expreſſed, with as ſhort breuitie of wordes as ye can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether without the offence of God, it maye be lawfull to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Churche of Englande, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe thoſe veſtures whiche at theſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20218:27"/> dayes they weare, and ſo be preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of the magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhether he that ſhal affirme that it is vnlawfull, or ſhal refuſe to weare this apparrel, offendeth agaynſt god, for that he ſaieth that thing to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane that God hath ſanctified: and offende agaynſt the magiſtrate, for that he diſturbeth the politike order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe queſtions, yf ye wyll make moſt briefe aunſwere, and ſende vnto me your iudgement as ſoone as ye may poſſibly, you ſhall do me great pleaſure. God be with you. From Lambeth the ſeconde of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:20218:27"/>
            <head>The aunſwere of M. Bucer to the foreſayde letters.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had receaued yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day towarde nyght, the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of your moſt Reuerende fatherhood, immediatlye I applyed my mynde to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, bearing in remembrance what I owe vnto your fatherhood, eſpeciallye in ſuche a matter, as is moſt agreeing to my miniſtery. Your fatherhood requireth of me, that I would write my ſentence with as much bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of wordes as I coulde, to the queſtions propoſed vnto me.</p>
            <p>I muſte needes confeſſe that I am verye hardely brought to vtter my iudgement to particuler queſtions in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſtitution of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſpecially ſuch as be intricated with great controuerſies amongſt godly men. For as the holy ſcriptures and dayly experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, Satan procureth all that he can, to ſet them together at variaunce with bitter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions in the articles of doctrine and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of Chriſte, eſpecially ſuche men who be godly ſtirred to receaue, and to reſtore the kingdome of Chriſt: whoſe godly endeuours
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20218:28"/> he laboureth, yf he can not make them quite fruſtrate, yet by his ſleyght to hynder them, whereby they ſhoulde not attempt a perfit reſtitution of the Churche, yf they ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their vttermoſt power. God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of vs that we ſhoulde worſhyp hym with all our heart, with all our ſoule, &amp; with our whole power, &amp; that we ſhoulde at once take vppon vs the ſweete yoke of his ſonne. Therfore now he calleth vpon vs by the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his iudgement, where he hath ſent ſo great lyght of his trueth, as at this day doth appeare, whatſouer vntowarde wylles men haue, that they can not playnely withdraw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them ſelues from his commaundementes, &amp; vtterly to reiect the yoke of his ſonne. Which matter Satan vnderſtandeth well inough, &amp; he is not ignoraunt howe fayne we would be gods by our firſt corrupted natiuitie, and howe we woulde gladly temper all religion to ſerue our luſtes and affections, therevpon he woulde perſwade men to go in a certayne meane (where as none can be in dede) that is, that men may refuſe and do ſome thynges at their pleaſures to ſerue their only lord God, which thinges yet he reputeth not ſo accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in them ſelues, nor man hym ſelfe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his affections to be brydled by them: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:20218:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> in ſuch thinges wherein the whole worſhip of God doth conſiſte, &amp; our whole ſaluation doth ſtande, our fleſhe being the very lumpe of ſinne and perdition, is wonderfully cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, for that he can not make hym ſelfe God, qualifiyng and moderatyng Gods eternall preceptes. With this craftie ſleyght, hath that auncient enemie driuen miſerable Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie vnto theſe preſent calamities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they be nowe oppreſſed. God forbidde, Chriſt Ieſus I ſay our only Saui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur forbid, that he preuayleth agaynſt Englande with this craftie ſutteltie. But now to the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons according to my duetie.</p>
            <p>Concernyng the former, this is my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, whiche I beleue I haue learned of the holy Scriptures. Firſt, I woulde not impart my aunſweres to any miniſters of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe Churches, but to ſuche as be the true &amp; faythfull diſpenſours of all the myſteries of God, ſuche as do labour to deliuer vnto the people, with great fidelitie, the whole goſpel of Chriſt, his whole doctrine and diſcipline, and labour to inſtyll it and beate it into their myndes. They that be ſuche Miniſters of the Churches of Englande, maye, as I thynke, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re with Gods pleaſure, thoſe veſtures which be at this day in vſe: and thei I thinke
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20218:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall do ſo muche the better after they hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preached the cleare doctrine of Chriſt our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour, with the detection and deteſtation, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well of the whole Antichriſte of Rome, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of any other aduerſarie to Chriſte: Yf the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then profeſſe by the wearyng of theſe ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, to haue no purpoſe at all to ſtabliſh any wicked deuiſes that Antichriſte hath ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>truded to the people: Nor that Prieſtes be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them ſelues more holy, or more able to paci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie God, then other Chriſtian men be: No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they preſent Chriſte to the father in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holy communion (as they vſe to affirme) o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they can applye his merite at their plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, by the vertue of the worke it ſelfe to any man, more then he doth receaue by his owne proper fayth, of the wordes and ſacramente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God. So that alſo he profeſſeth, that he thereby do not meane Aaronicall rites to be reſtored againe: but that he doth by his fact, perfourme only his obedience to the Kynges Maieſtie, and to ſuche whom God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to determine of theſe externall rites of the Churche, with common conſent by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worde of God, to this ende, that all offences of diſorder, and breache of publique conſent, may be auoyded: And alſo to proteſt that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature of God is good to Godlye men,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20218:29"/> yea alſo for ſignification. And therefore all true Godly men, may godly vſe thoſe rites, whiche wicked men haue abuſed, howſoeuer vngodly.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, to proteſt that they, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Kinges maieſtie, nor the great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Realme, meane to retayne or to cheriſhe any ſuperſtition in vſyng theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures. But foraſmuche as the vſe of theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, hath ben practiſed godly of the right holy fathers, before the Pope was Antichriſt of Rome, &amp; may at this day ſerue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſettyng forth of the holy miniſterie, and of the whole Chriſtian profeſſion, to the inſtruction of the younger and ſimpler people, ſo that there be a godly ſignification ioyned therevnto, and the ſame alſo godly taught. And that they declare, that the rulers woulde not remoue theſe veſtures, wherby they myght geue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the weaker in the fayth, to deſpyſe or contemne the true miniſterie of Chriſte: or els to geue them any ſuſpition by ſo doyng, as though thei were led with a certaine irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious leuitie, to ouerthrowe and aboliſhe al thinges vſed before in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea of thoſe thinges whiche may ſerue to ſome good vſe.</p>
            <p>And further, they may proteſt, that the people ought, in beholdyng theſe veſtures,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20218:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> to haue their meditation vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no other thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but vpon the heauenly puritie &amp; bryghtneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and of the apparrelling of all good vertue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whiche be bothe ſet out, and alſo be exhibit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to all true beleuers, by the holy miniſterie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Church, and that both they and their m<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſters woulde labour withall diligence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attayne to that brightneſſe and comlyneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that al at length may ſhine in the veſtures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> righteouſnes and ſaluation. And it behoue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miniſters to vſe ſome garments, not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> couer and to defende their bodies, but ſuch as may alſo haue ſome ſignification, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may admoniſhe them of ſome thing.</p>
            <p>Now therfore, foraſmuch as it is thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good to the Kinges Maieſtie, &amp; to the chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> councell of the Realme, to reteyne the vſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe veſtures for this preſent, they ought to chaunge the wicked abuſe of the papiſtes, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe good creatures of God in them ſelues, to ſome godly vſe, both to the glory of God and to the honour of the Kynges Maieſtie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo openly to declare, that all thinges to hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and good men, are holy and pure: And tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they be truely ſanctified by the worde &amp; pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, ſo that neither deuyll nor man can defy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any creature of God, but that godly me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may vſe them godly, &amp; to the glorye of God
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20218:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> yea euen for ſome vſe of ſignification, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the fruition of their naturall effectes. For all creatures may admoniſhe vs many wayes to conſider the creatour, both of them, and of our ſelfe, and of our gratitude toward hym, beſide the conſyderation of his large liberalitie, in reſpect of their natural effects: And to theſe admonitions, they maye and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught publiquely be vſed. Whiche ſentence of myne, I myght iuſtifie with diuers Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, beſides the example of the Apoſtles, whiche dyd ſo long vſe Moyſes ceremonies, without any impietie.</p>
            <p>As concerning the ſecond queſtion, this is my ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, gathered, as I beleue, out of holy Scripture. They which do ſay that it is not lawfull to vſe the apparrell that is in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, in any maner, yea in that maner which I haue deſcribed: I ſay, that they be at the leaſt in errour, for that they denie al thinges to be holy to them that be ſanctified.</p>
            <p>The ſame do I affirme of ſuche, which for the ſame cauſe wil not weare thoſe veſtures, foraſmuch as the vſe of them is receaued, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon ſuperſtitious or lyght cauſe: but by the publique lawe of the Realme, and by the conſent of the Churches. In dede the vſe of theſe veſtures maye be forced by ſuche ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20218:31"/> to pleaſure the Romane or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Antichriſt, as it is nowe in Germani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that it can not be godly admitted of the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly miniſters of Chriſte. For I muſte need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay, that they take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the godly Magiſtrate their due honour, which doth deny that the iudgement ought to be folowed in theſe ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters. Rom. 14. for that they do declare the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theſe garments to be obſerued of that co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſideration, which I haue a litle before deſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed.</p>
            <p>I truſt your moſte Reuerende fatherhoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wyl beare al theſe things wel in worth. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to anſwere to briefly &amp; to groſſely, I though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it a great offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, eſpecially for that I ſee wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what art Satan doth reſiſt, leſt that at once the whole religion of Chriſte ſhoulde be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored amongſt vs (as were neceſſarie) &amp; as all godly Kynges hath done their diligent labour, according to Gods preceptes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples whiche he hath declared by Moyſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Chriſte his ſonne, whyles Satan goeth about to ſtirre vp ſo many pernitious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of all the circumſtaunces of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aſwel in doctrine, as rites. For ſurely, except that we remoue ſo horrible and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyfeſt ſacrileges and diſhonoringes of God wherby the whole kingdome of the ſonne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:20218:31"/> God may be receaued, and we lowly ſubmit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur neckes to his good yoke: O howe intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable wrath of god ſhalbe kindled agaynſt this Realme. The Scriptures be full of ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xamples, as he doth nowe ſhewe moſt terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto Germanie. Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſiſt the Kinges Maieſtie with his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite, and be preſent with you the head fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers of the Churches, &amp; al the nobles of this Realme, that ye may both knowledge and embrace duetifully in time the dayes of your holeſome viſitation, and all other ſuch thinges in the whiche only ſtandes the peace and health of this Realme. God preſerue your father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Cambridge, <date>this tenth of December.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:20218:32"/>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:20218:32"/>
            <head>To M. Martin Bucer, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour in Diuinitie moſt worthy, his reader and maiſter moſt reuerende.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race and peace from the Lorde. &amp;c. For what cauſe I am now in trouble (moſte Reuerende) ye ſhal vnderſtand it by this meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in writyng. I praye you that you would vouchſafe ones to geue it the reading, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd yf that ye ſhall eſpye any errour therein, I deſyre you to ſignifie it vnto me by your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etters. If anye thyng hath ben vttered to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arkly, &amp; with fewer wordes then the cauſe requireth, I pray you, that you woulde ſet it out in the margent, with more light and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er wordes. If ye ſee the cauſe iuſt, and meete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or a godly miniſter, ſubſcribe therevnto in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ende I hartily pray you. I ſende you alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat I haue written before three yeres ago, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the .x. preceptes, that your worthyneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay knowe what my iudgement is in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20218:33"/> cauſe of diuorſe, I praye you vouchſafe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reade it, that if I haue erred in this parte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> humane ouerſight, I maye be aduertiſed your learning and fatherly admonition, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that I may refourme the ſame. I pray you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fatherhood therefore (and I doubt not but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall ſone obtayne) that you would helpe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Church in her conflict, by the great and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> notable giftes of god vndoubtedly beſtow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vpon you. I require the ſame of M. docto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Martyr, to whom (after your ſentence a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> prudent iudgement is knowen) this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenger whiche I ſende, ſhall repayre. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Lorde Ieſus long preſerue your worthyne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At London <date>the .xvij. of October. 1550.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in heart an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prayer all whole Iohn Hoper.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:20218:33"/>
            <head>To the Reuerende and learned father, Iohn Hoper By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, his good Lorde. Grace and peace through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Yght Reuerende, and in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt moſt dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I had purpoſed to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere before this tyme vnto the letters whiche of late I receaued from you: but I was ſo let with wayghtie and ſundry buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe, that I coulde not before nowe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liſhe eyther myne owne will, or your expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this behalfe: wherfore I beſech you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccordyng to your accuſtomable gentleneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd wyſedome, to take in good part this my delay. What ye haue written of the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie whiche is riſen betwene you and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight reuerende Lorde. B. of London, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing the apparrell of miniſters, I haue both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead it, as your requeſt was, &amp; alſo conſyder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t as attentiuely as I coulde for the ſhortnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the time. I ſay ſhortneſſe of time, becauſe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not retayne with me your writing but
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20218:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> only one night. For the meſſenger who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uered it vnto me, ſet foorth the next day ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the mornyng towarde Cambridge, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ye wylled me to ſend it (being once re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by him, vnto maiſter Bucer: Which thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dyd, both diligently, and without all dela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>In that litle time that I had to peruſe y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> writing, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended ſo al the matter, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> euen at the firſte I conceaued no ſmall io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your ſinguler &amp; earneſt ſtudy, in that you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your endeuour that Chriſt his religion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be brought agayne vnto a chaſte and ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> puritie. For what ſhoulde be more de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all Godly heartes, then that all thing by a litle &amp; litle, ſhould be cleane taken aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and cut of, whiche hath very litle or noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in them that can be referred wholly to ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather be iudged of the godly to ſuperfluous. For to ſpeake of my ſelfe, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hardly drawne from that ſimple and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, whiche ye knowe they of <hi>Argent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> haue vſed euer, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time that they refo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med their Church, where diuerſitie of app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rell in Churche miniſtration was aboliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For I haue alwayes alowed that pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſage that originally had imitation of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles Churche. And I beſeeche GOD mortall, that this maner may both ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:20218:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer continue, and alſo that whereſoeuer Chriſt his Church is refourmed, it may at length be receaued. You ſée that in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>taunce and chiefe poynt of the matter I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſſent not from you, nay I deſire with all my hart, that that thyng whiche you goe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bout to bryng to paſſe, may take place. And the moſt eſpeciall cauſe why I doe ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſire, is, partly for that I would we ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, as nigh as might be, to the holy Scriptures in rites and ceremonies, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olow the example of the Church, when it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as in beſt caſe and ſtate: partly for that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erceaue that thoſe that be geuen to papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rie, do goe about with theſe reliques to maynteyne at leaſt a litle ſpyſe of Maſſe, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be geuen to them, more then the nature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f indifferent thinges do require. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng, yet the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of theſe matters do not ſo farre carry me, nor the reaſons alleaged by you ſo perſwade me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at I ſhoulde affirme the vſe of ſuch ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures to be pernitious, or of theyr owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ature contrary to Gods worde: For I do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terly thynke it to be a thyng indifferent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd I am not ignoraunt that ſuch is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure of indifferent thynges, that at one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure they may be vſed, and at an other
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20218:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> time refuſed. To eate that is ſtrangled, of ſelfe is an indifferent thyng: yet it is mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſomtimes to refraine from the vſe therof, ſomtimes to vſe it moſt freely. And in this reſpect, though I haue ſaide this diuerſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of church apparel is not to be retained: n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, it to be wicked, I neuer ſo iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged, that I dare therefore condemne any ſuch whom I ſee vſe it. For if I had ben <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſwaded, I would neuer haue commun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cated here in Englande with the Church where ſuch a choyſe as yet is reſerued. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> although as I ſaid, I do very litle alow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neuertheleſſe I ſee ſomtimes in theſe ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t things that ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> although th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be greeuous &amp; burdenous (in that it is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lawfull to do otherwiſe) muſt be patient<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſuffered, leſt if men ſhould ſtriue for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more bitterly then it nedeth, that it wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be a let to the aduauncement of the goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; alſo that thoſe things which of their own nature be indifferent, through our heate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould be taught to be meer w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked: Which two things, except I am dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, bryng with them great and greeuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſcommodities. For if we could be conte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſuffer the Goſpel firſt to be ſpred &amp; dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye to take roote, without all doubt, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would better &amp; eaſlier be perſwaded to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moue
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20218:35"/> away theſe external rites. A man, ſo long as he is ſick, or is in his recouery, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is muche greeued that certaine ſmal and tryflyng thynges parteynyng to his meate and drinke, ſhould be debarred from him, which yet afterward when he is fully reſtored vnto his health, by him ſelf &amp; of his owne accord without any other mans coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, doth renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce them, as vnmete &amp; vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. Wherfore, let Englande be firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently inſtructed, &amp; confirmed in the chiefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt neceſſary poyntes of religion: then afterwarde by my iudgement, the Church ſhall not be muche offended to haue theſe thynges, ſomewhat ſuperfluous, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. But nowe where as alteration in the moſt neceſſary poyntes of religion, is laboured for, &amp; that with ſo much difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: yf nowe we pronounce thoſe thynges to be wicked, that be of themſelues indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſo much would the moſt part of mens mindes be alienated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, that from that day they woulde not find in theyr heartes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer after to heare with a good wyl at our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>andes ſound doctrine, and inſtructions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery neceſſary matter. Surely, Englande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much bounde vnto you, in that ye haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>boured more then a greate ſorte hath,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20218:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> in preaching and teaching. Likewiſe, in England you alredie haue obteyned much fauour and great aucthoritie, whereby ye ſhall be able to do much good to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of Gods glory. Ye muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heede, leſt ye ſtand in your own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way, contendyng to bitterly, and all out of tyme. Yet woulde I not haue you hereby gather, that my mynde is, that a Miniſter of Gods worde ſhoulde neuer contende for the maintenaunce of the truth and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Scriptures, I make no ſuch aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who dayly aſwell in publike as in pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uate diſputations, in waightie controue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſies, do take a part againſt the aduerſaries for true religion. But thys I ſay, we muſt take heede, leſt theſe thynges which be of leſſe importaunce, through our ſtrife, may be the meanes that thoſe thynges which ſhould be eſteemed of greater force and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, eyther can not at all be brought into the Church, eyther if they be once brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be eſtabliſhed with continuanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Agayne, yf we holde on in diſſwading t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe indifferent thynges, as pernitious, altogether wicked, we condemne with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very many Churches which haue receau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Goſpell, &amp; blame to bitterly innumer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20218:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> which a great while ago were counted worthy of all prayſe. Neyther am I igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, that the aucthoritie of Churches that be nowe, or hath ben, ought not to beare ſuch a ſway, that thereby the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Gods worde ſhould be trode vnder foote: Which (although the whole world ſhould runne to wrecke) ought to remayne wythout touch of breſte ſure and vnuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: yet for all that I iudge we muſt take heede, leſt that for thinges indifferent, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we condemne ſuch Churches as be now at this day, or thinke not wel of thoſe that haue ben long before our dayes. And for becauſe I perceaue that ye ſuppoſe theſe thyngs not to be indifferent, peraduenture it ſhall not be amiſſe nowe for to examine the reaſons that ſo ledde you: and that (as you do) I may do it in fewe wordes, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe matter to two chiefe pointes. Firſt of al, ye ſay that the Prieſthood after the order of Aaron, is not to be reſtored, wherunto theſe diuerſities of veſtures ſeme to parteine. For ſeeyng we haue Ghriſt to be our Prieſt, Aarons ceremonies be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erly abrogated, and therfore they cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e called agayne of thoſe that meane well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d godly. The ſecond foundation of your
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20218:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> reaſons, is, that theſe diuerſities of veſtures were inuented of Antichriſt: therfore we ought not only to forſake the Pope, but all his inuentions. Beſide this, ye would haue all maner of difference of veſtures &amp; appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of Miniſters to be taken away. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſeing theſe two be the cheefe ſtrength of your argumentes, I wil firſt entreate of them. Afterwarde, I wyll adde whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be, if I can cal to my remembraunce any other thyng, brought in of you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme your opinion.</p>
            <p>In Moſes lawe or Prieſthood, after Aarons order, there were ſacraments, with the whiche it pleaſed God to confirme (as I myght ſay, by putting his ſeale to them) the promyſes made of Chriſt comming. I knowledge and do graunt, that all theſe thynges be abrogated, neuer to be brought in agayne: for we beleue that Chriſt is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redy come, and not that he will come. And we haue other ſeales in ſcripture deliuered to vs of Chriſt hym ſelfe in the Goſpell, bread, wine, and water: therfore we neede not cal againe ſignes for this purpoſe vſed in the olde Teſtament. There were alſo in that lawe other ſignes and actions ſo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deyned, that they coulde not be properly
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20218:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> called Sacraments, and yet they had ſome reſpect to comelineſſe, to order, and to ſome commoditie. And theſe I iudge may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and retained, as thinges agreeing to the light of nature, &amp; inducing to ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable vſe. Who doth not ſée that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to the intent they that beleued might lyue more peaceably and quietly, did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the Gentiles to abſtayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blood and ſtrangled: And yet theſe thyngs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, were fetched from the order of Aaron, if ye wil comprehende generally all thynges whiche was in the olde lawe. And there is none of vs ignorant, but that the tenthes was fetched fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, which now in our dayes be appoynted to find the miniſters of the church thorowout Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. You cannot well proue by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the new Teſtament, that pſalmes &amp; hymnes were ſong in the church at pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſeruice, which thing yet appeareth moſt plainly to be done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Teſtament. I wil here omit that S. Ambroſe in his expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the .xiiii. Chapter of the firſte to the Corinthians ſayth moſte playnelye: that the maner of propheſiyng which Paul tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, was deriued out of the Synagoges,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20218:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> into our Churches. To theſe I could bring forth other thyngs, and that not a fewe in number (if tyme ſuffered me to conſider di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently the matter) which our Churche haue borowed out of Moſes decrees. And that I may ſpeake onely of holy dayes, which we keepe in memory of our Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> reſurrection, byrth and death of Chriſt, and Pentecoſt: ſhoulde we therefore aboliſhe them, becauſe they be the reliques of the olde law? You ſee, as I ſuppoſe, by al theſe thynges, how that not all that parteyned to the Prieſthood of Aaron, is ſo aboliſhed, that nothyng of it may be retayned or vſed of vs at theſe dayes. Nor here ye ſhall not by and by ſaye, that thys is nothyng els but to open a windowe to all abuſes, as to holy water, ſenſinges in the Church, and to infinite ſuch other: For the aduerſaries wyll ſtrayght ſhape you thys aunſwere. Fyrſt of all, that there muſt be limited a meaſure in any caſe, aſwell of thoſe that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſerued, as thoſe that ſhalbe brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne into the Church. And ſecondarily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that no opinion or vertue of religion is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all to be attributed vnto them, contrar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe to that we ſée is done of the Papiſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in theyr holy water and ſenſinges. Laſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:20218:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> all, there muſt good héede be taken, leſt our Chriſtian libertie be brought into ſome daunger, which ſhoulde be, in caſe if that ſuch thynges as be reſerued or reſtored, be appoynted neceſſary meanes for to obtaine ſaluation. For ſo are ſuch thynges to be brought in agayne, or to be tollerated, that they be layde away whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they appeare not to be put to good vſe. And ſo it ſeemeth to me, we muſt do at thys tyme with thys di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of apparell, according as I decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my mynde before. For I woulde, and now wyſhe, that they were layde aſide: but forſomuch as yet hytherto it hath not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled (vntyll better may be) I thynke we ought to beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if it pleaſed God, I woulde that the Churches of Germany myght redeeme their libertie with this one inconuenience, although I wyſhe by all meanes, that no ſuperfluous thyng ſhould be forced vpon them. But let vs conſyder your other argument, that is to ſay: It is not lawfull to vſe theſe kynde of veſtures, becauſe they were inuented of the Popes tyranny. In thys point I do not well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue how it may be affirmed for a ſuretie, that we can vſe nothyng that perteyned to the Pope, and is vſed in popery. Truely,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20218:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> we muſte take good heede that we bryng not the Churche of Chriſt into ſuche bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, that it may not vſe anye thyng that the Pope vſed. It is very true, that our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers toke the temples of Idols, &amp; turned them into holy Churches, where Chriſte ſhoulde be worſhypped: And they toke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſalarie and reuenues conſecrated to the Idolles of the gentiles, to their wicked ſhewes and playes, and to theyr holy vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries virgins, and tranſpoſed it to fynde the Miniſters of the Churche: And yet al theſe thynges dyd not only ſeruice vnto Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, but vnto the deuil. Yea the holy Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall wryters, dyd not ſtycke to take the Vearſes of Poetes, which had ben dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated vnto Muſes, &amp; to other diuers gods &amp; goddeſſes, for to be playde in playes, &amp; ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſhewes, to obtayne the fauour of their gods: I ſay they did nothing ſticke or feare to vſe them, when it ſeemed to them conuenient, imitating Paul the Apoſtle, who ſtocke nothing at al to rehearſe for his purpoſe <hi>Menander, Aratus,</hi> and <hi>Epimeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> and that he did in intreating the holy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſcripture, applying prophane wordes, to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forth Gods religion. We reade alſo howe that Wine was conſecrated vnto <hi>Bacchus,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:20218:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> Bread vnto <hi>Ceres,</hi> Water vnto <hi>Neptune,</hi> oile vnto <hi>Minerua,</hi> letters vnto <hi>Mercurie,</hi> Song vnto the <hi>Muſis</hi> and vnto <hi>Apollo,</hi> &amp; many other thyngs Tertullian rehearſeth in his booke, entituled, <hi>De Corona militis Chriſtiani,</hi> where almoſt he entreateth this ſelfe ſame argument. Yet for all that, we ſticke not to vſe al theſe thinges freely, aſwell in holye, as in prophane vſes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at one tyme or other before, they had ben conſecrated to Idolles and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils. Howbeit, I wyl not graunt, that theſe diuerſities of veſtures haue theyr begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges of the Pope,<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 3 Cap. 31.</note> for ſo muche as I reade in the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorye, howe that Iohn the Apoſtle wore at Epheſus, where he dwelled, a Byſhoppes apparell, tearmyng it, <hi>Petalum, ſeu lamina Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calis.</hi> As touching Saint Ciprian the holy Martir, <hi>Pontius</hi> the Deacon writeth, that a litle before he ſhould be beheaded, he gaue vnto hym that was appoynted to behead him, his veſture called <hi>Birrus,</hi> after he had put it of, and to the Deacons he gaue his other veſture called <hi>Dalmatica,</hi> and ſo ſtoode in linnen. Chriſoſtome maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whyte veſture of the miniſters
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20218:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Churche. Moreouer, the auncient wryters declare vnto vs,<note place="margin">In Mat. cap. 26. Hom 83. et ad po. Ant. Ho. 60.</note> that Chriſtians when they came firſte vnto Chriſtes religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, chaunged theyr apparel, &amp; for a gowne, they dyd put on a cloke, for the whiche cauſe when they were mocked of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, <hi>Tertullian</hi> wrote a very learned trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, <hi>De Pallio,</hi> that is to ſay, of a Cloke Neyther, as I take it, you be ignoraunt, that a whyte veſture was wonte to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to them that were baptized Wherfore it appeareth that before the Popes ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannye ouerwhelmed the Churche, ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was ſome maner of diuerſitie of apparel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Churche. But be it ſo, let them be the inuention of the Pope, as you would<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue it: yet notwithſtandyng, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the papiſticall inuention in them, I can not be perſwaded ſo muche impietie to be therin, that whatſoeuer it toucheth, it doth by and by ſo infect and corrupt, that it can not be lawful for good &amp; godly men to vſe it godly. I ſuppoſe, ye vnderſtande what my iudgement is, either in reſeruin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or bryngyng in agayne the Moiſaicall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> papiſticall rites.</p>
            <p>Nowe that I haue breefelye gone o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> theſe two cheefe poyntes of your reaſons
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20218:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> I come vnto that whiche ye alſo graunt: That al thynges inuented by man, be not forthwith to be reiected &amp; condemned. For what is it els but mans inuention, that we communicate at the Lordes table, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the mornyng, then when we haue dyned? It was alſo deuyſed by man, that the value of ſuche thynges as was to be diuided in the primatiue Churche, were layde at the feete of the Apoſtles. I graunt with you, that theſe choyſes of apparell do not of it ſelfe edifie: And yet for all that, other men wyll iudge it expedient that they be tollerated for a tyme, as though paraduenture by that meanes, theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions wyll be auoyded, by whiche it is in hazarde leſt greater benefites and more ample commodities be hyndered, and (as we ſee it falleth out) leſt mens mindes be withdrawen from the Goſpell. I wyll not here ſaye, that they whiche ſtande to the defence of this matter, may pretende ſome honeſt and iuſt ſignification of the apparell, and that not diſſentyng from the worde of God, whiche is this. The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Churche (as the prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie witneſſeth) be Angels and Gods meſſengers: but Angels for the moſte part
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20218:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> appeared, being clothed in white garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I pray you, how ſhal we debarre the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of this libertie, that it can not ſignifie ſome good thing, in ſetting forth their rites and ceremonies, eſpeciallye being ſo done, that no maner of Gods honour is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them, &amp; that they be in ſight come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in number fewe, and that Chriſtian people be not with them ouer burdened, &amp; matters of greater importance be omitted. Peraduenture you will ſay to me, Let Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Churche declare them ſelues to be angels, &amp; not repreſent angels by ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification. But Paul the apoſtle might ſo haue ben aunſwered, when he taught the Corinthians that it was meete that a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould haue her head couered, &amp; a man his head vncouered, vrgyng it only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſignification. For ſome man of the Church might haue aunſwered him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Let a man declare him ſelfe to be head of his wife, &amp; let a wife declare her ſelf to be ſubiect vnto her huſband, not in ſignes, but in deedes and conuerſation. But yet Paul iudged it a meete &amp; a profitable thing, that both of them, aſwell the man as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhould be moniſhed of theyr duetie by ſuch a ſigne or action. For by ſuch ſigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:20218:41"/> and meanes, we be ſtirred vp to do our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice &amp; duetie, for they bring into our mindes that whiche is decent for vs to do. And yf hereby the weakelynges take an occaſion of errour, let them be monyſhed that they be but indifferent thinges, and let them be taught, that no part of Gods honour and religion is placed in them.</p>
            <p>Now, whether the eyes of them that be preſent, be turned cleane away from thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſerious matters, becauſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of apparell, peraduenture euerye man wil not graunt it. Firſte the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries may aunſwere, that this ſhall not fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, if ſuch apparel be appointed that hath no gorgeouſneſſe, but is playne, and vſed before in the Church: For no man mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes at thoſe thynges that be dayly vſed, and of ſmall value. Nay it is more lyke, that men beyng ſtirred with the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of them, ſhall haue theyr cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more attentiuely vpon ſerious things: for the externall partes of the ſacraments, ſeeme to be inſtituted to this ende, that we euen of the very ſyght, and of our externe ſenſis, ſhoulde be inwardlye moued to haue contemplation of diuine thynges.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20218:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> Neyther ſuppoſe I by and by a tyranny to be brought in, yf anye thyng that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different ſhoulde be receaued into the Churche to be done, and that many ſhould conſtantlye obſerue the ſame. Nowe a dayes we do miniſter the Lordes ſupper in the mornyng, ſo that we wyll not receaue at all after dynner in the publique congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. But who wyll ſay that this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth of anye tyrannye, whiche we all do with one wyll and conſent? Truelye it woulde pleaſe me rather, (as I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes rehearſed) that we ſhoulde only do thoſe thynges that Chriſte dyd, and Paul delyuered: but yf there be ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different thynges added, I would not now therefore greatly contende, eſpecially foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as we ſee that they by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the light of the Goſpel is much aduaunced in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and dayly may be more aduaunced, do take part agaynſt vs. I graunt with you, that al which is not of fayth, is ſinne: Neuertheleſſe, that which is written of S. Paul to Titus, ſemeth greatly to ſerue for to eaſe and quiet the conſcience,<note place="margin">Tit. i. d.</note> that is: Al things are clene to the clene. And to Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. a</note> Euery creature is good. For it is not neceſſaryly required that we ſhould proue
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20218:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> euery particuler thing which we vſe, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely mentioned in the Scriptures. It is enough generally to know this fayth: That indifferent things can not corrupt thoſe that be of a pure mynde and ſincere conſcience in their doynges.</p>
            <p>Theſe thynges haue I briefly gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as touching the controuerſie whiche ye propoſed vnto me, out of the which, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche God with all my heart, that ye maye ſhift your handes well of. And I deſyre you to take in good part that I haue written: for if I coulde haue aunſwered eyther more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially, or more plainly, I would haue ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied your requeſt to my power. But for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to euery man to write handſomely and redyly of theſe matters, you muſt nedes pardon me. And aſſure your ſelfe further of this one poynt, that I am redy nowe and at all tymes to beleue the trueth, when I ſhall be otherwayes inſtructed. In the meane ſeaſon, thynke ye not that this iudgement which here I haue declared vnto you, was but nowe firſt perſwaded vnto me. For euen from the begynnyng, ſince that I applyed my ſelfe vnto the Goſpel, my minde was, that this difference of veſture ſhould be taken away, but yet ſo, that I dyd not iudge
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20218:43"/> it of their owne nature either wicked or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious. I beſeeche God almyghtie to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue you ſafe and ſounde, with al your houſeholde, through Chriſte Ieſus our Lorde.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <dateline>At Oxforde, <date>the fourth of Nouember. 1550.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours both in minde and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite wholy, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:20218:43"/>
            <head>Ampliſsimo domino &amp; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendiſſimo Symmiſtae Ioanni à Laſco. ¶ The Lorde graunt vnto vs in theſe troubleſome times of the Church, to begin and finiſhe al thinges, that offences and daungers be not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He more diligently I weygh &amp; conſyder, both what fruite we may gather by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie of veſtures, and alſo what Sathan goeth about thereby to worke: I woulde haue wiſhed before the Lorde, that it neuer once had ben ſpoken of, but rather that all men of our function had agreeablye &amp; ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gone forwarde and continued in teaching true repentaunce, the wholeſome vſe of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hynges, yea in commendyng and puttyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the apparrell of ſaluation. I ſee not in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fewe (alas I ſaye) I ſee marueylous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in abolyſhyng Amelech, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng ſtones, ſtockes, veſtures, and thoſe thinges that be without vs: when in their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20218:44"/> deedes &amp; whole lyfe they moſt ſtiflye retayne the whole Amelech ſtyll. I knowe alſo ſome that helpe foreward this ſtrife, ſo that in the meane tyme the chiefe and moſte neceſſarie poyntes are leſſe regarded and called vpon, that is: of remouyng ſacrilegious perſons from ſpoylyng of Churches: of prouydyng fyt miniſters for euery pariſhe: of the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of diſcipline againe. As for my part, if I thought thoſe ceremonies and veſtures were impure of them ſelues, I woulde not take vpon me in any wyſe the office of a Biſhop, vntyll by ordinarie aucthoritie they were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away. &amp;c. But to the purpoſe. I thinke it not impartinent vnto this matter, that we all be admoniſhed to take heede of Sathans accuſtomed ſleyghtes, wherby he leadeth vs away from the care of neceſſarie thinges, to the carefulneſſe of thoſe thinges whiche may be well let paſſe, and from the ſearchyng out of the true doctrine of Chriſt, to induce to vs thoſe thinges, wherein fewe can conſent a like, and finally, by the which he kindleth in diuers men a zeale to purge thoſe thinges which are without vs, therby to neglect our inwarde deformities. And ſeyng whatſoeuer we do either in word or deede, both priuately and publikely, we ought to do it in the name
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20218:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, geuing thankes by him to god the father: Surely it is our duety, no leſſe circumſpectly to beware that we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do nor leaue vndone any thyng, wherof we haue not ſure or certayne aucthoritie out of Gods worde, touching our actions and matters domeſticall and Eccleſiaſticall. It is alwaye and in all thinges ſinne, whatſoeuer is not of fayth of the certayne worde of God.</p>
            <p>But to conſyder this queſtion in it ſelfe, I haue, accordyng to my gyft, weyghed your reaſons, and yet I can perceaue no other, but that the vſe of all externall thinges, aſwel in holy ceremonies, as in priuate matters, ought to be left free to the Churches of God. I call that free vſe, wherein godly men vſe thinges created of God without any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, &amp; to a certayne edifiyng of their faith in Chriſte. I veryly (as I haue confeſſed vnto you, &amp; haue declared in deede vnto our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen) had rather that no kinde of veſture whiche the papiſtes vſed, were retayned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, and that both for the more ful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the Antichriſtian prieſthood, and alſo for playner aduouchyng of Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie: yea and to be ſhort, for the auoydyng of daungerous contentions among the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, (though notwithſtandyng I woulde
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20218:45"/> haue the Miniſters of Churches to vſe ſage veſture, and ſuch whereby they might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned from other men) but chiefly I would al the diſcipline of Chriſt to be in force amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs: Yet I can not be brought by any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (as farre as I ſee hytherto) to deny that the true Miniſters of Chriſtes Church, may vſe without ſuperſtition, and to a certayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> edification of fayth in Chriſt, any of thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures which the Antichriſtians abuſed. For what ſhould let, but that the Churches may vſe that white veſture, or more veſtures, to moniſhe vs preciſely of that diuine benefit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which he by the holy miniſterie of the church dealeth vnto vs, the benefite I ſaye of the light and dignitie of that heauenly doctrine: and by the whiche alſo the Miniſters them ſelues may be the more myndfull of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and had both for it, and by the admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that outwarde token, in greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of the common people of the church. Whether we wyll or nay, we are compelled to confeſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the enſignes of them that beare publique offices, helpe ſome thinges to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine &amp; increaſe the aucthoritie of Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; publique power, yf other thinges want not, by the which the true reuerence is geuen vnto them. For if theſe things be not ioyned
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20218:45"/> with thoſe enſignes, they induce not a vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but rather the ſinguler deteſtation of them, who vnworthyly vſe theſe notes of vertue. Signes in deede are ſignes, and not the thinges: yet how muche they are able to admoniſhe and moue the mind (God geuing the increaſe) he that obſerueth, wyll wonder.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, wheras otherwayes the true dignitie of Miniſters is euident, and yf any particuler church by publique iudgement do conſent vpon the retaynyng of certayne ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, only for the commending vnto vs of the giftes of god, which he geueth by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of the Church, &amp; for to put the yonger and ruder ſort in mynde, without all ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: Truely I can not ſee why ſuch vſe of veſtures in ſuch a Churche, may not ſerue to ſome commendation of the holy miniſterie, &amp; ſo conſequentlye to the edification of fayth. For what let is there, but at this day they whiche are indued with the ſame ſpirite of fayth, may vſe a few ſignes as godly, as the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t holy men haue vſed many? They had (you wyl ſay) expreſſe writing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the vſe of their ſignes. I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; in dede it made much touchyng the true vſe of their ſignes. But in that God dyd commaunde the vſe of thoſe and many ſignes, we certainly learne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:20218:46"/> the vſe of thoſe ſignes may ſerue (he geuyng grace) to promote true religion, and that it hath none vncleanneſſe in it ſelfe, or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: neyther can be by the abuſe of the wicked ſo polluted, that it can not be health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to godly men vſing it godly. Now when as god by his word hath ſanctified al things by our prayers, and hath made all thinges pure to the pure, what cauſe can we alleage out of the worde of God, to deny that God wyll not bleſſe ſuch vſe of ſignes (wherof we ſpeake) that it ſhoulde not be effectuous to that Churche to ſome commendation of the miniſtery, and therof alſo to ſome edification of faith? For how can it be, but that he which promiſed to bleſſe al the workes of our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des whiche we take in his name, wyll denye his bleſſyng to theſe ſignes, ſeeyng he hath no where forbidden ſuch a vſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as we haue expounded, and hath made vs Lordes of the Sabboth, &amp; all other thinges of this worlde?</p>
            <p>But if we graunt that theſe thinges which I haue ſpoken concernyng the vſe of ſuche ſignes, maye be: it is ſurely the part of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly charitie, commaunded vs by God, to leaue ſuch vſe of ſuch ſignes in ſuch a church, free, to the iudgement and conſcience of that congregation, except we ſee an open abuſe,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20218:46"/> eyther of ſuperſtition (as yf theſe thynges were vſed as conteyning in themſelues ſome part of godly worſhip of themſelues) or of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention (as if they diſpleaſed the greater and better part of the Churche) or of gettyng of good wil of ſome men, whom in theſe things we ought not to gratifie, becauſe they therby go about to bring a ſeruitude, vnworthy for Chriſtian men.</p>
            <p>It was euident at ſaint Paules tyme, by the moſt cleare Scriptures of God, that the vſe of dayes, meates, and all other externe things, was made free, &amp; it was a ſure token of infirmitie in faith to doubt thereof: yet the holy ghoſt pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth, that ſuch weaklings ought to be receaued, not to the troubling of their cogitations, and not to be contemned of the ſtronger in fayth, &amp; that in theſe thinges it myght be graunted to euery one to be ſure of his owne ſenſe, ſeyng that the Lorde had receaued theſe weaklynges.</p>
            <p>Nowe if the holy ghoſt woulde haue men to yeld ſo much to them which were in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt errour, inaſmuch as thei depended vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in the chiefeſt &amp; neceſſarie partes of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere religion: what ought to be graunted to theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> free vſe of external things, whom we can not conuict of anye errour by
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20218:47"/> Gods worde? For howſoeuer I examine and expende thoſe your two argumentes (that is: They are the imitation of the Aaronicall prieſthood, and the markes of Antichriſtes prieſthood, &amp; therefore ought to be eſchewed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue Chriſt) yet that thyng which you woulde, is not hereby concluded. For to imitate Aarons ceremonies, is not of it ſelfe vitious: but onely then when men vſe them as neceſſarie to ſaluation, or to ſignifie that chriſt is yet for to come to take fleſh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him.</p>
            <p>For yf by no meanes it be lawfull to vſe thoſe thinges which were of Aarons Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or of the Gentiles, then is it not lawful for vs to haue Churches, nor holydayes. For there is no expreſſe commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by word in the holy Scriptures of theſe thinges. It is gathered notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, from the example of the olde people, that they are profitable for vs, to the increaſe of godlineſſe, which thing alſo experience proueth. For any thing to be a note of Antichriſte, is not in the nature of any creature in it ſelf (for to that end nothing was made of god) but it hangeth altogether of conſenting to Antichriſtes religion, &amp; the profeſſing thereof. The which conſent &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion beyng chaunged into the conſent and profeſſion of Chriſtianitie, there can ſticke in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20218:47"/> the thinges them ſelues, no note or marke of Antichriſtes religion. The vſe of Belles was a marke of Antichriſtianitie in our churches, when the people by them were called to Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; when they were rong againſt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes: now they are a token of Chriſtianitie, when the people by them are gathered together to the Goſpel of Chriſt, and other holy actions. Why may it not then be, that the ſelfe ſame garment may ſerue godly with godly men, that was of wicked ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly? Truely I know very many miniſters of chriſt, moſt godly men, who haue vſed god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe veſtures, &amp; at this day do yet vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: So that I dare not for this cauſe aſcribe vnto them any fault at al, much leſſe ſo heynous a fault of communicating with Antichriſt, for the which fault we may vtterly refuſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with them in Chriſt. The Prieſtes of deuyls dyd celebrate in their ſacrifices, the diſtribution of bread and the cup, as <hi>Iuſtinus Martyr,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tertullian</hi> make mention. What let is there, why we may not vſe the ſame ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies alſo? You wyl ſay, we haue a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord touching this ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Very wel. And by the ſelfe ſame it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that ſame thing to ſerue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of god to the ſeruice of Chriſt, which the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20218:48"/> wicked abuſed in the ſeruice of Deuyls, if the commaundement of Chriſt be added therto. But it is the commaundement of Chriſte, that in our holy actions we inſtitute and vſe al thinges, ſo as comlyneſſe and order be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that fayth may be edified.</p>
            <p>Nowe yf any Church iudge and haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience (ſuch as I doubt not there are many this day in Germanie) that the vſe of ſuche veſture bringeth ſome commendation to the holy miniſtration, and therby helpeth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in the way of comlyneſſe and order, to the encreaſe of fayth: what (I pray you) can be brought out of the Scriptures, why that Churche is not to be left to her owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this matter, neyther therefore to be contemned, or to be called into queſtion for her iudgement ſake? That Churche veryly wil kepe in theſe thinges a meane agreeable to the Croſſe of Chriſte, and wyll diligently attende, that no abuſe crepe into it.</p>
            <p>If therefore you wyl not admit ſuch liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and vſe of veſture to this pure and holye Churche, becauſe they haue no commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lorde, nor no example of it: I do not ſee howe you can graunt to any Church, that it maye celebrate the Lordes ſupper in the mornyng, and in an open Churche, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20218:48"/> conſecrate to the Lord: that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes may be diſtributed to men kneeling or ſtandyng, yea, to women aſwel as to men. For we haue receaued of theſe thinges, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commaundement of the Lorde, nor any example, yea, rather the Lord gaue a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie example. For in the euenyng, and in a priuate houſe he did make his ſupper, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed the Sacramentes, and that to men only, and ſittyng at the table. But it wyll be obiected, that in England many vſe veſtures with manifeſt ſuperſtition, and that they do noriſhe &amp; confirme in the people ſuperſtition. Euen ſo (it maye be aunſwered) very many abuſe al this whole Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as alſo Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and all other Ceremonies. Therefore let vs withſtande this miſchiefe, &amp; vanquiſhe it vtterly. Wherunto though it may be that the taking away of veſtures may helpe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, yet to driue away all this miſchiefe, it wyl not ſuffice. Nay the Prieſtes themſelues muſt be firſt remoued, and in their roomes placed faythfull miniſters in the kyngdome of Chriſte, ſuche as be learned in deede, and godly affected. To this therefore, to this I ſay, muſte we chiefely endeuour our ſelues, that the heartes of the people may be purged by fayth, whiche fayth is firſt begun and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20218:49"/> by the hearyng of the worde of God: this hearyng is brought by the preachers of the Goſpell. Suche therefore let vs call for, and that there maye be ſtore of them, let vs be earneſt for reformation. Let there be a viſitation of the vniuerſities, whence many fit miniſters for Churches maye be gotten. Let vs neuer ceaſſe to crye out agaynſt that Sacrilege, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fatteſt benefices are graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vnworthye men, in reſpect of their worldly ſeruice: that the pariſhes are ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably vndone through papiſtical ſleyghtes &amp; violence. Theſe, theſe I ſay, are certaynely papiſticall factes, agaynſt theſe ought we chiefely to bende our force: but to be ſtout and earneſt againſt ſtones, ſtockes, veſtures, and ſuch other thinges, which of them ſelues nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bring gayne, pleaſure, nor honour, it is a very eaſie matter to the hearer and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, eſpecially thoſe that be diſcharged from papiſticall ſuperſtition, for by the ſhaking of ſuch thinges, great mens ſtomakes are not offended. But to remoue Churche robbers from the ſpoyles of Churches, and to do all thinges poſſible to this ende and purpoſe, that euery pariſhe may be prouided of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient miniſters, &amp; that Curates may haue ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for their ſuſtentation, &amp; to ayde them
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20218:49"/> to the full reſtitution of Chriſtes diſcipline: This is a thing of great moment: This is a harde thing to all them which are not able to ſay with ſaint Paul:<note place="margin">Phil. 1. c.</note> For Chriſte is to me life, &amp; death is to me aduantage. And againe, God forbyd that I ſhoulde reioyce, ſauing in the croſſe of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, wherin the world is crucified to me, &amp; I to the world. It pleaſeth me right wel, that al Antichriſtes iraſhe ſhoulde be remoued away, as farre as might be. I meane not only his enſignes and markes, but all his ſteppes and ſhadowes in what thing ſoeuer they ſeeme to ſtand, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in ſtockes, ſtones, garmentes, or whatſoeuer other thing els it be. But let vs endeuour our ſelues to baniſhe firſt the body and ſubſtaunce of Antichriſt, and then after, his enſignes, ſteppes, and ſhadowes. The body and ſubſtaunce of Antichriſte, conſiſteth in the wycked deſtroyers and ſpoylers of Churches, by whoſe meanes, not only Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes diſcipline, but alſo al the whole doctrine, is oppreſſed and put out of place.</p>
            <p>When I conſyder theſe thinges, &amp; againe looke backe (as I ought to do) towarde the preceptes of the Lorde, and his examples: I wyſhe with al my hart, that as many of vs as wyll be Chriſtes folowers in deede, that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:20218:50"/> euen ſo we earneſtly go about to reſtore hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> kyngdome, as the Lord himſelfe went abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to begyn it, &amp; that we ſeke it before all othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thinges, and let the preachers in all doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and diſcipline inſtruct the people, and be ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> who for our Lorde Chriſtes ſake &amp; the prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chyng of the Goſpel wyl be redy to leaue al: that by theſe mens miniſterie we bryng th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> people to the kyngdome of Chriſt, and let v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appoynt to euery flocke their owne faythfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhephearde, who may labour no leſſe to cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agayne the true notes and markes of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtianitie, as to aboliſhe vtterly the marke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; notes of Antichriſtianitie, which I would wiſhe ſo aboliſhed, that there remayned no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo much as the memorie of them in any mens heartes. But ſeeyng that this thing can not be brought to paſſe, vnleſſe Chriſtes kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be fully receaued, I woulde wiſhe that all we ſhoulde to that ende beſtowe all our ſtrength, vnto the which worke, for as much as we neede many workefelowes, I would<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiſhe (with all ſuch as truely loue the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ieſus) that we ſet apart all diſſention, and ioyne in one perfect concorde, to endeuour our ſelues to ſet vpon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon aduerſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> We ſee now, being taught by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> experience o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo many yeres, that the Lorde graunteth bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:20218:50"/> to a few, to depart from that ſentence whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they haue once faſtened them ſelues in, ſpecially if they haue alſo contended for the ſame: ſo that we ſhalbe enforced either to diſſolue chriſtian Communion with many whom the Lorde hath receaued, or els we muſt geue place one to another, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that eyther of them may reſt in theyr owne iudgement, though the other diſſent. It is a verye harde thyng in deede, yea to moſt holy men, to denye them ſelues, and he is ſeldome founde among men, whiche woulde not be content rather to yeelde in his patrimonie, then in the opinions of his witte. Nowe then wheras we ſee almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God to beare this our infirmitie in vs ſo mercyfully, fye on the hardneſſe of our heartes, yf the example of our Lorde &amp; God can not encline and mollifie our heartes, to the like mercy and patience. Wherefore I conclude, that we ought to take great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent heede: fyrſt, that we take not vpon vs ſtrayghtway, to determine al queſtions as they ryſe, yea, let vs ſturre none at all which throughly tend not to the kingdome of Chriſt. Let vs acknowledge the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our witte and iudgement. Let vs ſtand in feare of our naturall arrogancie,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20218:51"/> and our peuiſhe ſelfewyll in our owne inuentions. All thinges neceſſary to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, are ſet forth vnto vs openly, clearely, and plenteouſly in the holy ſcriptures, and in the ſtudye and perfection thereof, euery one of vs wanteth verye muche. Let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour then to fulfyll, and once to make vp our imperfection with godly ſtudies. Of al other matters, let vs diſpute moſt warel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> let vs define moſt ſlowly, or neuer, let vs ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende at no tyme. If at any tyme thorowe the craft of Satan, &amp; our owne negligence, variaunce ſhal ryſe in theſe thynges, let vs betyme leaue of from the ſame as ſoone as we can, by whatſoeuer way we may, or els let vs make ſome truiſe in them. Seldom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is there any victory obtayned: yea neuer holſome victory gotten.</p>
            <p>Hereby (moſt godly ſir) you ſee vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly what is beſt to be done, both in this controuerſie of veſtures, and alſo of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of other ceremonies. I had rather then much goodes this queſtion had neuer ben moued: but nowe ſeeyng it is moued, I wyſhe it to be geuen ouer, and deferred to ſome other tymes.</p>
            <p>Theſe your two argumentes: <hi>It is a peece of Aarons Prieſthood, and therfore
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:20218:51"/> contumelious toward Chriſt now exhibited, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s then glorious, when he was to be exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited.</hi> Secondarilye, <hi>Theſe are notes of Antichriſtianitie, and therefore not to be vſed of men geuen to Chriſtianitie.</hi> Theſe reaſons (I ſay) conclude not in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that whiche you toke in hande. For we borowe many thinges godlye from the orders of Aarons Prieſthood, to the glorye of Chriſt now exhibited. So many things which the Antichriſtes haue made markes of theyr impietie, may be tokens of the kyngdome of Chriſt, as the ſignes of bread and wine, the water of Baptiſme, the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of handes, preachynges, Churches, Holydayes, and many other thynges. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo theſe places of Scripture are of a great ſcope. The earth and the fulnes thereof is of the Lord, not of the deuyll, not of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, not of the wycked. And agayne, The ſonne of man is Lord of the Sabboth,<note place="margin">Mat. xii. a. Mar. ii d. Titus .i. d. i. Tim. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and the Sabboth is made for man, and not man for the Sabboth: And all thyngs are pure to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure: And euery creature of God is good, nor can be defiled to good men, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he abuſe of euyll men. The worde of god muſt be folowed in all reſpectes, aſwell in our priuate actions, as publique. For all
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:20218:52"/> thynges are to be done in the name of the Lorde Ieſu, and to the glory of God. Then ſuch libertie as we graunt to our ſelues in our priuate vſe of externall thynges, let vs not denye in publique. The true ſpirite of Chriſt, goyng about to ouerthrowe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, ouerthroweth fyrſte thoſe thynges whiche are cheefe and peculier vnto by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. For firſt the ſpirite of Chriſt endeuoryng the reſtitution of Chriſtes kyngdome, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreth fyrſt doctrine and diſcipline, whiche be the cheefe &amp; peculier poyntes of Chriſtes kyngdome.</p>
            <p>This colourable craft of Satan alſo muſt be taken heede of, by the whiche he bryngeth to paſſe oftentymes, that eyther we recken thoſe thynges ſinnes which are no ſinnes, and thoſe that be ſinnes in dede, we ſeme not to regard them in our ſelues: Or els agaynſt thoſe ſinnes whiche our conſcience define to be ſinnes in deede, we vſe no ſuche ſoueritie as we ought.</p>
            <p>The Lorde graunt that you, ryght wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypfull frende, may religiouſlye weygh theſe thynges. I knowe you ſeeke the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of Chriſt, &amp; I haue heard of you, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I reioyce, that you are carefull of your iudgement, ſo that you dare not ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:20218:52"/> recken the ſame for ſure and certaine, though you ſeeme to folowe playwelye the worde of God, thynkyng with your ſelfe that you are a man, and that you may ſlide out of the way.</p>
            <p>Therfore I deſyre and beſeche you by the croſſe of the ſonne of God, by the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Churches whiche are at this day ouerwhelmed with calamities, by the deſired conſent that we ſhoulde ſeeke to raigne in all Churches, by the peace that is in Chriſte Ieſu: Agayne, I deſyre and beſeeche you, that you do nothing raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in this queſtion of ceremonies. You haue ſeene weake members in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Saxonie, you haue ſeene alſo many thinges for the which you geue God than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. Let no man therefore, except it be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon great neceſſitie, caſte of thoſe, whom the Lorde hath ſo notably taken to hym. O would to God the ſtate of the Churches of Fraunce, Italy, Poleland, were brought to this poynt. Let vs in this Realme take moſt godly heede, that we further not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares the deuils intentes, who throweth in among vs ſundry queſtions and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies: leſt we ſhoulde take in hande to handle the queſtion of ſetting forward the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:20218:53"/> doctrine of the Goſpell, and reſtoryng of diſcipline, &amp; thereby to remoue all Drones from Eccleſiaſticall and ſcholaſticall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries. This Sathan, when he can not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the order of Byſhops wholly in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice vnto hym, he goeth about vtterlye to abolyſhe this order, and by that occaſion ſo to ſpoyle the Churches, that whyles due ſtipendes want, the holy miniſterie may be committed to the vileſt of the raſkall peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Let vs take heede of theſe cogitations of Satan, and let vs withſtande them as muche as we can, by the power of the Lorde, and by no meanes vnaduiſedly to helpe them forwarde. Fewe we are which ſincerely profeſſe the Lord Ieſus, and none of vs there is, which is not oppreſſed with much infirmitie: therefore let vs receaue one another, as the Lorde hath receaued vs. Let vs yeeld mutually one to another, as the Lorde hath yeelde to vs, which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and duetifull loue, if it beare ſtroke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, we ſhalbe able with one ſpirite, and one mouth, &amp; with our whole might, to diſcomfite the body and ſubſtaunce of Antichriſt. And ſo afterward without any offence of the good, &amp; with certayne edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith among the children of god, we
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:20218:53"/> may bryng to paſſe the vtter defacing of al the markes, ſteps, &amp; ſhadowes of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>O Lorde Ieſus, thou our onely peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, aſwell with the father as betwixt our ſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anniſhe out of our mindes whatſoeuer draweth vs in ſunder, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer darkeneth the cleareneſſe of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among our ſelues, whatſoeuer by any way hyndereth the abſolute concorde in thy miniſters in defence of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; in deſtroying the tyrannie of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt. Powre into our mindes thy holye ghoſt, which may leade vs into all trueth, who graunt vs to ſee and take in hande al one thyng: but firſte of all that whiche is cheefeſt, whereby the ſtrength of thy kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may be reſtored vnto vs, and al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges parteyning to Antichriſt, may clene be blotted out of all mens heartes &amp; memory. The goodnes &amp; loue of the ſonne of God, for his infinite loues ſake towardes vs, vouchſafe to geue vs theſe thinges, to the glorye of his name, to the ſaluation of his elect, and that the wycked ſay not ſtyll, Where is theyr Chriſt? Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Deditiſſimus tibi in domino Martinus Bucerus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20218:54"/>
            <p>Imprinted at London in Powles Churchyarde by Richarde Iugge Printer to the Queenes Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20218:54"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
